the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University
today I'm talking to Jordie Sullivan
Jordie is a dietician who has worked
with many of the best athletes in the
world in a variety of sports he's also a
practitioner having participated and
competed in many Jiu-Jitsu Ultramar
marathon and other endurance events
jordy's clients as I mentioned are some
of the best and the best you're talking
about many UFC world champions other
individuals like Ned Brockman who
recently ran a thousand miles in 12 days
so jordy's knowledge of the Practical
aspects of fueling for performance are
really unparalleled in this conversation
we talked a lot about the details how
much water how many grams of
carbohydrates what type of carbohydrates
and as many other details as I possibly
fit in to exactly how do I fuel
performance or just getting enough fuel
to exercise for people not competing in
sports Jordy did a fantastic job in this
conversation outlining how this does
change in different scenarios with
different goals and populations and
people so while Jordy has spent most of
his career with these Elite high-profile
athletes he's also been coaching
non-athletes for well over a decade and
that comes through really clearly in the
conversation so please enjoy this
conversation with my friend Jordie
Sullivan Jordie Sullivan welcome to the
show man Andy thanks for having me I've
followed your work for a long time it's
in my opinion that no one even is close
to rivaling you in your area so uh
really appreciate you being here we're
going to cover a lot of areas we
globally call like sports performance
fueling but I actually want to start
with two things really quickly and I
want to see if you even know what they
are so this is a little bit of a
challenge to you so let me read this one
actually that I have written down for
you um okay number one yogurt with
berries and honey number two meal
chipotle chicken with rice and avocado
number three Tiara massu dates uh with
oatmeal number four lobster roll number
five a sports drink number six lamb Rice
Bowl number seven a banana with honey
all that in one day do you know what I'm
talking about I have a I have a good
feeling what you're talking about yeah
tell us what that what actually is yeah
so last weekend I participated in my
first hro competition and if you don't
know hro is kind of the new age CrossFit
so it's a it's a mix of strength Sports
and then Endurance Sports so the setup
is you run 8 kmers as fast as you can
and then you jump in and out of these
stations so yeah me and my team went
down to Melbourne and um did that and
that was the the fueling PR going into
it so it was really you ate all of that
in one day prior to competition yeah
we're going to have to go through that
in detail and don't want to know exactly
why you ate that cuz my guess is you
weren't just sort of eating whatever you
had in front of you and trying to
consume as much food there was a little
bit of intention and strategy with the
food items the calories the
macronutrients split uh the time you ate
that all that was was very strategic I
assume yeah there were definitely goals
behind it I'll be honest though that was
my first competition so a lot of that
was just self-experiment wor of that
type of competition with that type of
competition right same as you Andy like
you work with so many different types of
athletes a big one for me is like if
telling these athletes hey go eat this
way and then I'm saying hey man have all
this food before you go and compete I
kind of want to know what that feels
like because so many times I've done it
where hey go eat x amount of
carbohydrates before you go do this
wrestling class and it's like there's no
way I'm having two bowls of cocoa pops
and three sandwiches before I go there
because what's going to happen start
rolling start wrestling around and so
going through that is um yeah just a bit
of self- experiment but there was a lot
of logic behind that and I think it
pretty well we'll go through it all
right great um And to clarify that was
not your first competition you you've
been competing in Jiu-Jitsu for many
years you've done a a large number of
endurance events ultramarathons and so
on and so forth which which we'll cover
I want to read a second one to you uh
which I think is a little more
interesting because I think you can hear
that and go well that's great if I'm
going to do this crazy endurance events
I could probably eat like that but I
can't eat like that all the time uh you
know I don't do things like that so
maybe let me turn to is something that's
maybe a little bit more realistic
sounding all right let me read this one
to you number one a protein mousse cup
with almond butter and berries number
two grilled salmon and pineapple salsa
three protein chocolate and almond mud
cake four jelly beans five parmesan
chicken and six coconut cookies and
chocolate do you know what I'm talking
about there yeah that's the El fought
Weg prodical this is a full day menu uh
this would be 1,00 calories 60 G of
carbohydrates 140 gram of protein and
125 gram of fat this is an actual meal
plan that you gave one of your highlevel
UFC fighters during the week in which he
was trying to lose probably what 10
kilos 8 kilos yeah 10% of his body white
for that for him that was about 13
pounds I'll say 13 pounds or so and so
I'm pointing this out to say I don't
think people think if I have to lose 10
lbs in a week that I would be eating a a
daily meal structure of protein powder
mousse cup with almond butter grilled
salmon chicken chocolates and jelly
beans and yet somehow you've managed to
get all of your highle athletes on
weight fueled correctly how in the world
is it possible that you can eat like
that and lose that kind of weight while
still performing yeah and I guess we'll
go into it but like you said that was
one for I think that was Kai France one
was K France yeah I was going to say
definitely sounds like a Kai type of
meal plan Kai is one of the most elite
UFC fighters in the world but when UFC
fighters compete and you know this Andy
you might be walking around at 180 lb
but when you weigh in for the UFC you
might be 150b so there's 30 lb
difference between what your natural
walk around weight is and then what your
contracted fight weight is so that meal
plan is actually part of a strategy
where what we're doing is we're trying
to strategically move water weight from
their body and it's part of a two-part
process where we'll go through what's
called a fight Camp which is eight weeks
of training really intense mixed martial
arts training which involves anywhere
from 1 to 4 hours a day of training and
what we're doing during that process is
we're strategically losing body fat and
so we can lose up to 5 to 10% of their
body weight just in that period and then
what we do is we move into the second
phase which is that diet where we
completely shift these macronutrients
around and the goal of that is to shift
10% of their body weight again but
instead of losing body fat what we're
doing is we're pulling fluid from
different compartments in their body and
the way that we do that is by changing
the macronutrients the problem
traditionally with UFC fighters is
instead of eating like that they'll just
eat chicken breast nuts water and
they'll do that three times a day and
anyone that has any enjoyment with food
will do that for about two meals and go
this is terrible and so I guess that's
our job right as we come in and we go
look we've got these principles we know
what we're going to do we know we can do
that how do we make this whole
experience so much better for you not
only is it it makes it the food way
tastier but just mentally like being
able to look forward to a meal like that
instead of boiled chicken and some
almonds and going oh God it just makes
it so much better and then that just
flows on to this whole performance
principle we have that we want to get
this guy going into this cage Peak
physical condition Peak mental condition
and that's just part of the process
today's episode is sponsored by momentus
momentus makes the highest quality
supplements on the planet period while
much of the supplement industry is like
the wild west with terrible quality
standards and minimal testing every
single one of momentus products is
third-party tested to ensure quality and
many are even NSF certified for sport
while I love all of their products I'm
going to focus right now on why I'm
particularly impressed with the new
momentous grass-fed way Protein Isolate
powder first as I've discussed many
times on this podcast it's really
important that you get at or close to
one gram of protein per pound of body
weight to help optimize things like
muscle growth and lean body mass but
this is often times really challenging
for people to do and this is where
things like momentus as wayy protein can
be a complete Lifesaver while many
protein powders out there have been
found to be contaminated with high
levels of things like lead or hormones
momentus is way protein is as pure as it
gets it's sourced only from grass-fed
European dairy cows and is cold
processed to maintain an optimal amino
acid profile and is completely free of
gums stabilizers and refined sugars it
is truly the best and highest quality
protein powder in the world now nobody
has to use supplements and I hope you
never feel pressured to do so but if you
are interested in using supplements it's
important that you get them from the
highest quality provider possible so
that's why I stick exclusively to
momentus if you'd like to give momentus
a try go to liv.com perform to get 20%
off your order again that's Liv mous.com
perform to get 20% off today's episode
is also sponsored by element element is
an electrolyte drink mix that has an
ideal electrolyte ratio of sodium
potassium and magnesium but no sugar
hydration is critical to Performance
both physical and mental performance
countless Studies have shown that even a
slight degree of dehydration even as
small as 1% can lead to decreases in
physical output and mental performance
we also know that electrolytes are
critical to proper hydration which I've
been harping on for years but you can't
do that proper hydration by only
drinking water you need to get the right
amount of electrolytes in the right
ratios and that's why I'm a huge fan of
element in fact many of you will
probably remember that I featured
element in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration nearly 5 years ago
I featured element in these videos
because they're blend of 1,000 mg of
sodium 200 Mig pottassium and 60 Mig of
magnesium really is unique and different
than any other electrolyte on the market
and has great scientific support I use
element constantly particularly when I'm
sweating a lot and I routinely make it a
part of my client's optimization
programs if you'd like to try element
you can go to drink LM nt.com perform to
claim a free element sample pack with
the pures of any element drink mix again
that's drink LM nt.com perform to claim
a free sample pack one of the many
reasons I wanted to have Yana and and
chat is because you can come with and
you can look at the research papers and
you can go over basic physiology and you
can understand how many calories to give
somebody there is some discussion there
but for the most part this is not
incredibly complicated you can then set
a macronutrient guidelines so how much
protein how much carbohydrates such like
that you could probably pull all that
from academic courses and papers but
then how do you put that together in
food how do you make that something
where somebody can as you mentioned
enjoy that sustain that how can that be
sustained while they're not also
compromising long-term minerals and
vitamins and how do we put together
structures in the case of the UFC
fighter is a little bit Niche right like
not many people are going to cut a bunch
of weight for five days but the concepts
and the learnings we can get for that I
think extend to everybody so whether I'm
fueling right before sport performance
or exercise whether I'm fueling my day
whether I'm in a caloric deficit whether
I'm in a caloric Surplus and so I really
want to to ask as many questions as I
can and learn from you about how do we
do that part right how do we do the art
of taking the science there and then
making it into a practice that makes
life so much more enjoyable so uh we're
going to get into all those things if if
if you're so willing uh and a bunch of
other stuff but I I think to get it
started maybe will'll wind all the way
back you use a term a lot that I love
that I want to ask you about and that is
performance nutrition so can you just
walk us through what is the difference
between nutrition as we normally think
about it and and how you and your team
Define performance nutrition yeah I
think when we think of nutrition like
you said it's food right and food is
integral to our life we are what we eat
quite literally the body that we're in
is made by the food that we eat and like
you said you can just break that down
into Little Numbers you can break that
down into your macronutrients you can
break that down into an eating plan and
it can be quite boring but when we look
at performance nutrition we need to look
at it a lot more holistically it's like
yes there's the physical food and we
need to break that physical side down a
bit more in depth than just the
macronutrients we're looking at okay how
does Andy Galpin what are the goals in
his life and how can I best fuel him to
achieve those goals whether Andy's a UFC
fighter whether Andy's an ultra
endurance athlete whether Andy's a busy
CEO just looking to perform his best in
the boardroom meetings relating with his
staff whether there's a stay-at-home mom
everyone has different goals that you're
trying to achieve and your food can play
an integral role in that but each person
each one of those Andes is going to have
a slightly different plan and slightly
different strategy based on those goals
and that's just the physical side of it
and like you alluded to earlier yes food
is just what we put in our mouth and you
can just dial it down to numbers but
it's so much more right like we get so
much enjoyment from food and you'd know
like it's the festive season one of the
best parts about Christmas is sitting
around with your family right like it's
that connection as well so it's like how
can you incorporate food so it's a bit
more than just the meal plan just
numbers just plain boring chicken rice
and veg how can you make a plan that
achieves the goal of this individual
does it so they can perform at their
best but do it in a way that they love
it and that food doesn't become this
boring monotonous thing and it helps
them holistically yeah I love it one of
the reasons why we called this show
perform it's many the same sentiments
right it's not athletes it's not sport
but it is you all want to perform a
certain way you gave a bunch of
different examples of that and what we
can glean from your definition of you
know performance nutrition it is saying
great let's just take our entire fueling
strategy and gear it towards how we want
to perform and you define those terms of
perform you tell us the restrictions the
equations and all that stuff and that
will just help you make that a better
experience overall I'll admit I am quite
terrible
at this part I am definitely much more
of the here's chicken broccoli and you
know an ounce of almonds and can get the
get the heck out of here that's why I
don't write the meal plans for our stuff
because it's it's not a particularly
enjoyable experience but um that's great
so performance nutrition in your
perspective is pretty clear how is that
different than something like periodized
nutrition so I guess when we're talking
about periodized nutrition you're more
talking about sporting performance right
so like let's take for example UFC guy
just CU we're on topic so that UFC
person might have a training schedule
that requires them to train 20 to 25
hours a week so what I would do and I
would come in as the performance
nutrition I'd go okay what's the goal of
this say training block let's say we're
in a fight camp we need to lose weight
he's got to lose a crazy amount of
weight 10 15% of their body weight as
part of that I've got to work out okay
this is his weekly calorie budget so I
need to periodize
a weekly calorie budget for this person
to hit this weight goal each week and as
part of that they're going to have this
training schedule which varies right so
Monday might be a very intense day
Tuesday maybe not so much Wednesday is a
really intense day Thursday uh moderate
Friday rest day Saturday very intense so
they're going to have all these
different training intensities
throughout the week and it's my job to
come in and go okay I've only got this
small amount of calories to work with
how do I best allocate these is and
that's where this idea of periodizing
nutrition comes in where I go okay Andy
just got signed to the UFC he's making
his debut he's got this crazy training
schedule we got 25 hours of training but
he's only got a calorie budget of
anywhere between 1,800 and 2800 calories
a day so how can I best shift those
calories in those different fuel sources
so that and is performing the best he
can in those training sessions probably
even more importantly how is he recing
between those training sessions you can
only train as hard as you recover and
then how can we best support the
adaptations that we want to get from
those training sessions and that's what
we mean when we talk about periodized
nutrition so what you've described is a
a weekly CH a daily change rather in
fueling particularly in energy overall
energy based upon Demand right so um
does that periodization then change from
week to week like if you were to compare
that to something like periodized
strength training where there's a
day-to-day variation but then there's
also hey this week to next week volume's
going to go up 5% or intensity or
something like that um in these cases
when you've got say four to 10 weeks
whether it's a UFC fighter or any of
your other many types of athletes you
work with or even nonathletes that
matter do see yourself generally
plotting out those weeks in advance as
well or do you do you like to see how
the week goes and then make the changes
kind of week to week yeah it's
definitely a give and take type scenario
because and you know this just as well
as Me Andy you're going have have the
theoretical best idea in the world and
and then what how does that play out in
practice and food as well as one of
those things where I can write it on the
meal plan I can have this great
communication but did you do it yeah and
I find with a lot of people when you go
into this periodized model and say for
an athlete we go okay the goal here say
we're not in a fight Camp we're not
losing weight let's just say we want to
get you really really strong fast
explosive we're really focusing on that
high intensity training and when I look
at that I okay that's your glycolytic
system which means you need to have a
lot of carbohydrates on board that's the
predominant fuel source we want to get
all these enzymatic changes that help
you get up there and stay there so I'm
looking for the volume of training that
you're doing and the intensity that
you're doing it at this is the nutrition
goal and if that's the nutrition goal I
need to look at that and go okay how do
I best fuel you for that when we're with
our top level athletes we have some
really cool systems where we can do
weekly testing where we can see okay
you're these strength testings
theoretically you should be getting
stronger if we're doing this and we're
doing this training theoretically you
should be getting fitter you should be
able to be doing more and we can go even
to the weeds of punches thrown each
round with our Elite level boxers you
should be getting better if we're
training these systems they're the type
of things that we're monitoring but at
the end of the day every athlete's still
a human right so it's like you need to
have that feedback with them where we
can look at the labs and we can look at
the numbers and we can go Andy's
tracking really really well but then you
come back and go Jordy I'm fried I just
can't do this and then I look at it and
I go man Andy's got six more weeks of
this what do I need to change to make
sure that he can keep going because the
overarching goal of this is to get
whatever this x adaptation is if Andy's
telling me that he can't even get
through the training for the next 5
weeks we're not going to get that
adaptation so even though in theory this
works out perfect okay I need to come in
me and Andy need to get together we need
to get with the strength coach we need
to get with the head perform coach we
need to figure out a new system and
figure out where is it lacking and it
may not always be the nutrition right
like there's so many other things that
go into performance could be your sleep
could be your hydration energy levels
stress you may have had a fight with
your partner the night before or
something else some financial problem
going on and that's leaking over into
that so we have to be aware of all of
those things because that's what's going
to determine how we progress and they're
all going to affect how we monitor your
performance so we need to be aware of
the system holistically so that when we
do track it we have some like
quantifiable data to be able to go yes
this is working this is not working I
know recently at one point you had three
current UFC world champions so Alexander
vinoski Israel and Leon Edwards right uh
fortunately unfortunately enough I have
a strong tie to banowsky you and I got
to coach against each other um hopefully
we'll get a chance maybe done line to do
it again it's always fun but you're
managing three different people at that
time in addition to all your other Elite
athletes and things like that you don't
need to give us any information about
them personally but
how how much of a range at that highest
level of performance do you see with
things like compliance did they eat the
food that they were supposed to eat uh
are they all at when they get to world
championship are they you know within 5%
of the calories you tell them are they
you know I assume we're all up there but
what does that look like from an
individual variation yeah yeah I won't
name individual names because this is an
example that I always use right like
I've been very fortunate enough at one
time they were 2 three and four
pound-for-pound best fighters in the
world and that's incredible that's there
is one other human that is better than
them at that Sport and that's incredible
you took the five pound-for-pound best
UFC fighters in the whole world you were
coaching three of the of the five yeah
exactly and that's and it's incredible
yes from like okay great for your career
but also from the science standpoint
right to look at it because in theory
yeah these guys are all following the
same principles we're using the same
fueling periodization principles are
similar but they we're changing for
their training schedule three very very
different humans and as you alluded to I
always use this as a great example one
of them very very strict I'd say 99%
compliant followed his meal plan did
everything right when we're talking
about periodizing he made sure his
pre-training carbs were good his
intraining cars are good whatever we did
postwork out was amazing hydration sleep
everything you name it he did it next
person was probably about 80 20 of that
mostly good few snacks here and there
sleep would be a bit bad probably stayed
out a bit late than what he should have
and then one of them really not that
compliant really not that comp nice way
to say it yeah that's probably the
nicest way to put it the thing is though
is that when you look at that
performance just on the surface you're
going wow that's three of the five
powerful pound best fighters not even
just UFC fighters best fighters on the
planet and when it came to their
performance it's like wow they're
performing at the absolute best but when
it comes to what I do with the nutrition
we've probably got one guy that's very
very good one guy that's probably about
here and one guy that's not good and
then me as their practitioner you
obviously make allowances for that we'd
always never ever Miss weight with any
of them but what you tend to see then
and this is probably a very interesting
conversation we can get into to it's
everything else that happens outside of
that and what makes up their performance
and a big one is say injury rate how
often are you getting injured and at
least me sitting in this seat working
with these guys I can tell you that this
guy did not get injured nearly as much
as this guy the guy that had the high
compliance the guy that was really
really good with his diet sleep recovery
never had got injured but never as
consistently illness sickness even other
things M training sessions training
sessions even sleep quality we've done
sleep studies on them and it's like it's
very very clear like but at the end of
the day we're still getting a very very
very high level performance and I think
it just shows two things I think
performance is very complicated no
matter how you want to Define it I think
it gets more complicated the more
factors there are in sports and I would
classify mixed martial arts as a very
multifaceted sport it's complicated
let's say running running is say a
single faceted sport that has some
considerations very very very
multifaceted mixed martial arts so
there's obviously lots of other
components that are making up this
performance but then I go but what
happens after these guys retire and then
we've got all these same habits that we
built here in the most successful parts
of their training years now they've got
to live with them when they're not
training so what do we do now and that's
where I think okay our responsibility in
this performance nutrition doesn't just
extend to the periodized nutrition to
the training nutrition you have to be
teaching these guys skills for the rest
of their life because it's very very
well known especially in the wrestling
world we see when wrestlers retire they
tend to put on a lot of weight yeah and
the most simple basic reason for that is
they keep all of the habits from when
they were an extremely active probably
extremely successful College wrestler
but then they have kids they get a job
life gets in the way we get busy you
might go to the gym here and there but
the activity comes down but the eating
habits stay the same and all of the
other Habits Stay the same as well so
you see this like Downs slope where we
go okay we're getting all these health
problems we're putting on weight getting
these deficiencies because you can get
away with it when you're just training
really really really hard but you can't
get away with it later in life so it's a
very very interesting example that I
always use it's yes even though at face
value you might be performing at your
absolute best what's happening under the
hood and I think it's our responsibility
as their performance team yes we need to
get a great performance but we need to
make sure everything under the hood is
still looked after I love the saying of
in theory there should be no difference
between theory and practice and practice
there is right so what's a just in your
experience with your athletes and with
your non-athletes so your regular folks
that you coach as well what's a
reasonable adherence I think 8020 gets
around a lot personally as a company
what we promote is 9010 9010 and the
reason that we say that is
because that 90% shouldn't be something
that's extremely rigid either it
shouldn't be something like like you
said where we have this meal plan and
it's like God I got breakfast what's
breakfast a dry eggs yeah a glass of
water okay what do I have for my snack a
dry protein bar oh God you know it
shouldn't be so rigid that oh man this
is horrible and then the activity that
you're doing you're going oh God my
trainer wants me to do a high Rock
session and I hate High rocks I just
want to go for a walk or I don't know I
want to do gymnastics if it's that
system it's going to make it very very
hard but if you set this up like we
spoke about to make it a holistic thing
and you work with the person in front of
you and you don't just go hey there's
all the theoretical numbers and you go
let's take this and mold it to this
person's lifestyle their goals their
needs their wants their situation their
financial situation and you create an
environment where we go okay how can we
stick to this 90% you can do that in a
way where it will happen it just has to
suit their lifestyle so instead of
having boring plain chicken okay let's
do a yogurt bowl with berries and let's
add some protein powder and let's make
it exciting and hey you've got kids how
can you make a meal as well and get the
kids involved so it's like a family
thing and we're enhancing that way hey
you don't want to do these crazy
high-intensity workouts do you like
swimming oh let's let's figure out how
we can get you to the pool do the kids
swim let's integrate this so if you can
do all that and make this part of your
lifestyle sticking to it 90% of the time
becomes much easier and we say 10%
because in reality we're always going to
have a Christmas lunch we're always
going to have a Thanksgiving dinner
we're always going to have a birthday
there's always going to be something and
you need to be able to give yourself
that allowance to not feel the guilt and
shame that comes with oh my God I
cheated on my diet I did that I didn't
get the workout in it's like life
happens life's busy you've got things
going on 90% of the time you you're
killing it it's all right go have a beer
with your dad at the pub go enjoy like
Christmas lunch with your family it's
fine you're killing it most of the time
life happens that's why we like to say
90% 10% leave it for those little things
10% is actually a reasonable number that
still gives you many feedings throughout
the week that are not off plan so if if
I'm tracking that right 90% would be
sort of the gold standard probably not
where most people are but that's where
you guys are aiming towards 80 20 is
probably enough to get most people
pretty good
results 75 is like we're not getting
anything or we're still getting some
like where's the bottom end of that
Spectrum where you're like okay if
you're here then you need to change
things and by changing things we
probably mean systems your system things
like that right we need to change the
approach would you say like 70 75 is is
that cut off point or is it lower where
someone would say it's a lot lower I
think if you're doing absolutely nothing
and then if you go to do something
that's a lot better than nothing right
and it's a probably just a scale and I
think where people get mixed up is they
don't know how to integrate it into
their life but if you're not exercising
you're not eating any nourishing foods
and say nourishing is going to be
different for say an athlete in an
everyday person but let's just say
you're just eating whatever you can
there's no thought there's no logic
behind it you've got other priorities if
you're not doing any of that and then
you just go okay I need to increase my
protein increase my hydration and I'm
going to aim for 10,000 steps a day
there's going to be big gains to be had
from that and there's it's like that old
saying in Jiu-Jitsu if going from the
couch onto the mat is far harder than
going from white belt to blue belt and
if you're at the bottom and you're
absolute Ground Zero with your health
and fitness going from that to even a
white belt in that area is very
difficult but you'll get really good
gains from it and then it's just a scale
up so I was going to say a number it's
it's tough I think yeah 9010 very very
uh idealistic but something's better
than
nothing is there any other core
principles that you always like to
follow regardless of the person
regardless of the goal or do you think
we've covered most of those already I
think we could probably give numbers and
I think I'll explain why we give those
numbers for these principles right and I
think the way I look at it if someone
comes in and again when we've got Elite
performers athletes it's it's a bit
different because again we're using this
periodized approach like I use with that
example Performance isn't always the
healthiest thing but when we're talking
about just the everyday Joe Like You and
Me Andy there's a few things I like to
tick off and I think they're probably
Universal goals and principles right
where most people want to be able to
live into their old age and be healthy
be strong be able to play with their
grandkids and be able sound of mind
enough to be able to hold conversation
and then be overall have a pretty good
sense of Health right like overall their
ticket's going to be pretty good and
then when I look at that I go okay if
that's the goal I could probably break
these down into some pretty lwh hanging
fruit that you probably should pick off
and if you do that chronically over time
it'll set you up for that pretty well so
I'd say like let's think about it if you
want to grow old you want to say be
strong be able to carry the groceries in
play around with your grandkids your
muscle is going to be really important
and so what's the main thing we need to
think about from a nutrition standpoint
with your muscle is protein so I think
that's the first and foremost the
easiest thing that we can just say okay
if I want to write myself a diet and
just get started here let's get a good
amount of
protein now Dr stew Phillips not sure if
you're familiar with him oh yeah know do
very yeah stew I I love Stew's
philosophy I love the the philosophy
stew has against not against the RDA but
the that 0.8 grams per kilogram or 0.3
grams per pound probably not enough no
and I would say as a base 1.5 G or about
0.7 G per pound of protein great place
to start it's still pretty low still
pretty low great place to start easily
achievable I know some folks when you
hear prot recommendations a lot of
comments I get back are like that's so
hard to get to that number but the
numbers you gave her are would be not
that challenging to get to very very
easy to get to couple feedings if not
two feedings a day you could do that I
think the next one that a lot of people
ties up them is just your overall
calorie intake and I guess we can get
into the Weeds about this a bit more but
and we talk about calories in calories
out and energy balance I like to think
of it the energy availability which
essentially just means how many calories
does your body have after it accounts
for all the activity that you're doing
in your day your metabolism everything
else how many calories do you have
available to fuel your body and it would
make sense that you have enough to make
sure all your bodily systems are working
your immune system your lungs your heart
everything else your muscles bones you
have enough calories to support those
body systems and that made sound really
simple but it's quite hard in reality
right and people will go okay well how
do I know what's right for me and am I
doing too much and we know if you do too
much over time that can cause weight
gain and then there's metabolic effects
that are associated with that so how do
I get that right so understanding that
and going okay Andy these are probably a
good range for your calories to be
aiming for you know what here we go
let's add this protein in the next thing
I would say is like okay well let's get
some fat in there we know Fat's
extremely important for the body very
very important for your hormonal Health
how much fat do we need I would say
lower end that I would take for my
Fighters 0.5 G per kilo that's
exceptionally low though yeah that's a
very exceptionally low so I would say
even for the average person you're
looking up to 1.5 G per kilogram even
then we've got a lot more wiggle room
and I go okay well let's set that and
then that's your fat that you can put in
this theoretical diet that you're
looking between .5 and 1.5 I'd say at
the lower end and even come up 1 to 1.5
let's stay around there and then we go
okay carbs and then everyone goes oh my
God carbs the demon word carbs and I go
look because the first thing that
everyone says they go oh carbs aren't
essential if I'm not an athlete I don't
need to be using them I go you know what
you're right but it we also don't need
to be driving Teslas down the 101 but
like they're there and we use them it
makes life a lot e easier the thing that
I first and foremost I talk about with
people when it comes to carbs I go the f
word fiber I go carbs are such a great
source of fiber and we know it's
probably one of the only things we know
in nutrition that if you have a certain
amount of fiber for a certain period of
time for a long period of time it's
hugely beneficial to your health so no
matter what your views are on these
carbs if you're just setting up your
bare bones diet use the amount of carbs
to get at least 25 to 30 G of fiber a
day yeah and then we go okay well then
we've got this really cool structure and
that's not even talking about okay let's
getting micronutrients you've just got
your bare bone structure here so from
there we can go okay I've set my
calories I've got an upper and lower
limit for protein fat depending on what
your lifestyle is you might go okay I
need more carbs for this activity I
don't I don't particularly like carbs
whatever but make sure you're getting
this amount of fiber and when you do
this activity with people you'll usually
go okay Andy we broken down these
numbers all of that if you do the upper
limits of all of these macronutrients
you eat enough carbs to get 30 gram
let's say we're trying to hit 2,000
calories but then we work it out and we
go Andy actually with the activity and
everything you're doing you need 2400
you go you've got an extra 400 calories
to play with and then you'll go Jordy
what's the what's the best way for me
what do I do here and I go well what do
you like and I go this is where we can
start setting up this 9010 principle cuz
if I go you go to me Jordi man I just
don't really like eating a lot of fat
like it doesn't matter Andy doesn't
matter pal here's the plan get more fat
in probably that 90% is going to start
to slip but if you say hey Jordy you
know what I'm hitting all these numbers
but I just love having more protein in
my diet I go man we got 400 calories to
spare you know what let's bump this
protein up let get L protein you can go
for yeah and you can just bump it up and
that's how we can make this more
relevant to you but I think using a
structure like that just to get your
bare bones framework is really useful
and it's really really useful because it
doesn't use a lot of diet ideology
either so you can have this conversation
with people who love keto who love
Carnival who love animal-based and you
can make it work for them and I think
that's where you get this adherence and
compliance from where hey you know what
I don't really care what you love you
and it's okay you can love keto you can
do whatever like you said as long as
we're testing this over time making sure
your bio Market are good you're
performing and whatever it is you need
to perform in eat whatever way you want
but let let's tick these main things off
and then let's look to optimize once
you've absolutely nailed this so
starting with protein for the most part
having a sense then of total caloric
intake playing with different
combinations of fats and carbohydrates
to balance the final number um within
that though probably in the neighborhood
of 10 to 14 grams of fiber per thousand
calories which is going to net you at 25
to 30 35 for most sort of people so if
you get those that sort of predetermines
the kind of carbohydrates getting for
the most part right you're not going to
get 30 grams of protein a day in jelly
beans like that's going to be or 30
grams of fiber and jelly beans that's
going to be pretty tough so by default
there you're setting almost a little bit
of backdrop for quality of food so how
at this point is this is when food
choices come in and food quality or how
do you think about that yeah exactly and
it's a it's a funny area right because I
feel like especially nutritionist
dietitians my position is that Whole
Foods are important I really do think
Whole Foods are important because what a
stun but and because I've been fortunate
enough to work with these Elite level
athletes like I said Andy where I've
seen okay this guy eats mostly Whole
Foods this guy doesn't and I've worked
with him for six seven years and we're
we're testing everything and we're
seeing and we're going man this this
does make a difference and the reason
that we set that up and we say hey
carbohydrates let's get 25 30 gram like
you said very hard to get 30 grams of
fiber from jelly beans yeah tough very
very tough so it sets up this backdrop
of okay we probably need to include
these Whole Foods and I'm not saying you
need to eat them all the time a big
philosophy that I practice by and I'll
steal these words from Dr Graham close
from Liverpool John is that Whole Foods
first but not just food alone yeah and
what that means is that yeah we want to
choose Whole Foods but at some point the
food's not going to be the best option
to fit these goals and I think a great
examp example of this is [__]
monohydrate Whole Foods first for sure
but if you're loading [__] monohydrate
do you really want to be eating 3 to
five kilos of steak a day probably not
realistic right maybe some people I
would love it maybe some people yeah
maybe for some but that's an example
where we go yeah Whole Foods first but
not Foods alone so let's just take that
back and let's just have a couple scoops
of [__] here I think whey protein is a
great example of that as well where we
go oh man like we want to get 30 of
protein here let say a chicken breast a
small chicken breast and we go oh if I
don't want that if I'm eating seven to
eight of them a day I don't want to get
to this much protein let's just have a
scoop of whey protein here it just makes
it so much easier especially when it
comes to these Elite level athletes or
just people who train not even Elite
level athletes we work with what I call
Professional amateurs which and everyone
knows them everyone has them at the
office you know the guy way too into
triathon he comes in it's the man what
we call them the mammals the middle-aged
men and Lyra don't get me wrong big fan
and I'm an endurance guy so I get it but
they are training basically like a
professional athlete going to be very
very difficult for them to eat 4,500
calories complete Whole Foods and
achieve the training nutrition goals
that we've set out for them so I really
do I believe that whole food should make
up the bulk of your diet but there is a
time and place for these more processed
foods today's episode is brought to you
by Parker University
if you haven't heard yet I moved my
research lab teaching and all academic
activities to Parker in mid 2024 and
could not be more excited about it
Parker is one of the fastest growing
universities in the country because the
facilities technology and student
experience are truly unrivaled I've
honestly never seen anything like they
what they built at Parker University on
top of that we're currently building a
64,000 ft² Human Performance Center that
will push the boundaries of sports
science and human potential Parker and
the human performance center are
physically located in Dallas Texas and
feature Elite academic programs in 35
healthc care Fields such as human
performance strength and conditioning
nutrition Chiropractic and much more but
we also have incredible undergraduate
and graduate tracks that are fully
remote meaning you can get a master's
degree from me in strength and
performance from anywhere in the world
the human performance center will open
later this year and feature
groundbreaking research and scientific
capabilities immersive student
experiences a visitor center dedicated
to human adaptability and resilience and
a suite of services that are open to the
public so all of you who've emailed me
over the years asking to come to my lab
to get some testing done now you can all
do that to learn more about our ecademic
programs at Parker set up an in-person
visit or attend one of our incredible
seminars visit parker.edu one more time
that's parker.edu today's episode is
also sponsored by eight sleep eight
sleep makes Smart mattress covers with
cooling heating sleep tracking and more
I've personally been sleeping on an
eight sleep mattress cover for years now
and it's absolutely glorious I love it
so much that I hate traveling away from
home because it means I can't sleep on
my eight sleep pod 4 ultra as you'll
hear me talk about endlessly on this
podcast there really is nothing you can
do that makes more of an impact on your
health and performance than getting
tremendous sleep and getting great sleep
requires having your body temperature
drop a couple of degrees at night and
that's hard to do on your own the eight
sleep has been a GameChanger for me
because I run hot at night or as my wife
calls it I'm a furnace if I don't have
something like an eight sleep helping me
cool down I'll wake up in the middle of
the night overheating and not feeling
great this is something I've also found
in many of the people that I coach
especially those who are really
physically active the eight sleep pod 4
ultra has two times more cooling power
yet is virtually silent and it has High
Fidelity sleep tracking and even has
snoring detection that'll automatically
lift your head a few degrees to improve
proove airf flow and stop your snoring
if you'd like to try eightsleep go to
8sleep.com
perform to save $350 off your pod 4
ultra eight sleep currently shifts to
the US Canada the UK select countries in
the EU and even Australia again that's
eight sleep.com
perform okay somebody shows up to your
door uh whether they're the I forget the
acronym you just use but the the guy who
likes triathlons way too much that's I
love that no offense Rob uh uh
the the other person the professional I
think fine doesn't matter what should I
be testing what should I be paying
attention to before I start my fueling
program my performance nutrition
strategy what do I got to have first so
if you're walking in if we've got the um
overe excited triathlete comes through
the door robs come through the door yeah
no offense so first thing we need to do
is let let's start with just the
calories right and and Andy you've
probably got access some to some amazing
metabolic equipment right but people
like you and me who have access that is
very much the minority we can't just
take the everyday person and say hey go
get a resting metabolic rate test and
we'll figure out exactly how many
calories is that what you like to do for
your folks Absolut if we've got if we've
got Elite level athletes who have access
to that and it's not a financial burden
to them which adds to the stress of the
whole situation for sure I'd love to be
able to do that the reality how avable
are those in Australia usually this is
the thing not very I would say unless
they're a UFC athlete who has access to
the performance Institute we're probably
not going to be able to get them them
some of our New Zealand based athletes
New Zealand high performance if you're
close to the Australian Institute of
sport maybe but outside of that very
very difficult to get them done okay cuz
it's pretty it's pretty easy to get it
done here in States yeah like you're
generally probably $100 200 bucks so
that test would be pretty easy to get
done so ideally you'd like to see
something like that if you can I mean if
you if you can go down the road to the
physio or the doctor's surgery and you
can get that done for sure because it's
going to give you a pretty good number
other than that you've got to use what
we call the standardized equations which
range there's so many of them in you
know the Harris Benedict so many types
of them basically what they're doing is
taking all this population data and
going hey based on your age weight
height and a couple other factors this
is how many calories we think you should
be having per day Y and we'll put direct
links to all that of course everyone in
the show knows but these are free
calculations right Google them you can
go in there and enter a pretty minimal
amount of information typically height
weight demographic stuff and it'll tell
you then how many calories you're
burning throughout the roughly exactly
and and you just go to Google and
calorie calculator to be honest Andy and
I'll explain why we do this is that you
could use all of these and when I'm with
a very specific audience say the
fighters the [__] equation is something
that I think is very very accurate but
for the everyday person I don't think
that's necessary if we dial that back to
that energy availability okay I want to
make sure that I'm getting enough
calories to support my body but not too
little that we're kind of burning
everything down but not too much that
you know we're putting Surplus and
putting our stores away and putting on
body fat is that 5% is that 12% is that
15 what what's a rough number there for
body either way uh Surplus or deficit
like how much are we looking to get them
so
four if we wind back and we say let's
just say I'll establish this and I I
just give it an equation where I go take
your body weight in kilograms and sorry
for everyone in Pounds divided by 2.2
and then if we just take it in kilog if
you can times that just by 40 the number
40 you get a pretty good estimate and go
that's my daily calories so if I weigh
70 kilg times it by 40 and there we go
and then we've got our calories and you
go oh is that that accurate and you go
the thing is unless we're in a
controlled metabolic environment we're
never going to know if it's that
accurate the way that you figure out if
it's accurate is based on what happens
after you put it to use a little bit of
a flag here we can test resting
metabolic rate in our lab we have a
bunch of other Technologies we can use
in other ways to do it
and we still do exactly what you're
going to talk about like it doesn't
matter you can take that data that I'm
that I'll share with you you can take
your body weight in kilograms multiply
by 40 and I'm telling you right now
you're you're going to be in about the
same starting spot we're in and because
it's next part that matters and that's
exactly what we've seen I've had so many
athletes go get tested at performance
centers and comes back and we go did I
really need to just send them off to do
that when I could have just done this C
and then spent two weeks tring this out
and narrowing it in is honest the only
time we do that is if we have really
high pressure uh like the first time
we've ever worked with an athlete and we
have short notice or they've had
troubles in the past or like something
like that where it's like they're really
nervous about it they're scared there
has to be some really additional
circumstances going on for us to do that
for that exact same reason I pretty much
can I know where you're going to be at
anyways and none of that matters until
this part so we don't do it very often
even though it's pretty accessible be
because the next part so that's a great
starting point when we go we go back to
your goal so say if you did want to go
into a deficit oh hey Andy comes with me
I want to lose a bit of body weight
before we go into the Christmas period
okay we need to set a deficit the rule
we use is about 10 to 15% from that
number that you get 20 2800 calories is
what we calculated a second ago 70 kilos
by 70 multip by 40 2800 and you want 10
to 15% lower than that number exactly so
you're going to cut off 300 calories
exactly 320 calories something like that
maybe touch more yeah maybe up to four
or 500 calories right but something in
that ballpark yeah and then the next
natural question that people go is hey
I'm exercising a lot I do this how do we
account for that and it is important you
do account for it don't get me wrong the
more you exercise the more you burn you
do need to think about that M I think
for most Everyday People if it's just
the everyday person coming into the
office and we're doing this with it
matters a lot less than say if we're
with an elite level athlete who's
training 25 plus hours a week right and
I think a lot of the time a lot of the
struggles I see in my practice with just
everyday people when it comes to weight
loss is they can't wrap their head
around this oh my my Apple watch or this
says this and my garment says I'm
burning this much and I'm eating this
many C and I'm just not losing weight so
this is the I looked at my watch it told
me I burned 700 calories but somehow I'm
not losing weight exactly and they go
and the reason I don't love that
approach is because I see the mental
stress that that causes and how dis they
get with the whole process I had a
gentleman come in and he said man I've
been doing this you know I've got this
charity boxing event I really want to be
in good shape for it he's super
motivated all his friends are behind he
goes man I'm like I can't figure out how
to lose weight I'm only eating 2,800
calories and this is a big gentleman
fairly inactive I said what are you
doing he goes oh I'm in the garden I'm
doing gardening and then I'm on the
pushbike for 30 minutes my my smart
device is telling me I need 2800
calories in a deficit and I'll just kind
of have to break it to him and go oh man
like I have professional athletes who
want to lose more weight than you and we
don't even go like I wouldn't go into a
2800 C they got to go way less than that
to lose weight yeah and they're doing
five times as much activity as what
you're doing so you need to take that
with a grain of salt and this comes back
to this point like we're saying you can
test all of this and there's equations
where you can go okay we've got this
Baseline number I punched in my body
weight times 40 I need to account for
the activity that I'm doing let's times
it by 1.4 1.6
whatever the best way and the safest way
to figure out if you're in that deficit
put it to practice control as many
things as you can control in the
calories outside which I'm sure we'll
talk about as well as the calories in
the food and we'll also talk about why
it's important to understand truly what
you're putting in and then if you do
that
consistant and you lose the weight
you're in the deficit and then we can
monitor from there and that's by far the
most time efficient and accurate way to
do it and it may not be the sexiest
answer because people will go surely
Andy galp and Jordi Salin give me the
test I can do give me the equation that
gets it hang on every time and it's like
that's not possible this is the best way
if someone was doing this and they were
saying all right um I calculated my
stuff it's 2,800 calories I want to be
on a 500 calorie deficit that puts me
somewhere in that 10 to 15 range so that
brings me down there um how do I know if
that's working what am I specifically
looking at let's say I'm four or five
weeks in Jordy what should I be paying
attention to that'll let me know I'm in
too much of a deficit or I'm not in
enough deficit yeah so if you just look
at overall average weekly weight loss
which is what you should be doing so we
say when you weigh make sure you weigh
at the same time in the morning you
weigh after you use the bathroom and in
the same or lack thereof clothes that
you use every week so if you can be
consistent with your weigh in get good
data very very good right like get very
very good consistent data as well
because you want to make sure Tuesday
morning is my day that I weigh in
because what you do on Thursday night
will skew what Friday morning is and if
you want to do daily weights I'm not the
biggest fan because we have these daily
fluctuations sodium training hydration
status food fiber exactly and again
it'll play in that mental side and can
be very disheartening take the weight
same day we like a Tuesday morning
especially if you're training you like
once a week weighs once a week weighin I
like it and then we can take a monthly
average and go okay if you're four weeks
in how much did you lose and let's say
Andy you're on the 500 calorie deficit
from your starting weight I can then
work out a percentage from that weight
how much did you lose per week I like
500 just as an example here because if
you were in a true 500 calorie daily
deficit you should be on almost exactly
a pound a week yeah right that's where
that number should be again it's just a
starting place on idea so what you're
saying is you would look at that
four-week graph and say okay we should
be down about 4 pounds total exactly it
might be 1.5 one week then 0.5 the next
week it'll be it'll jump even from week
to week but on aggregate you should be
looking at about a pound is about a
pound per week I know it changes based
on size but is that a you know half a
kilo per week I it's a very safe number
I think if you want to go one step
forward and really make it for yourself
I go what is that as a percentage of
your total body weight because we know
that say if you're losing more than 2%
of your body weight per week very very
doable Andy you and I have done that
with many many athletes but it's not
sustainable and we know that because you
see this all the time when people go
crash dieting and they lose weight too
fast it's easy to get off but it's not
easy to keep off yeah and what we like
to recommend to our guys is if you can
lose 0.5 so half a percent to 1% of your
body weight per week based on our
experience and what we know based on
this energy availability model where
you're not putting so much stress on
your system you should be able to do
that in a way where over this extended
period of time whatever fat comes off
your body you should be able to keep it
off because all of the problems that
come is when you try to do this too fast
and you and I know this very well
working with these Fighters when we get
like you said these short notice fights
and you can do it someone comes into you
Andy and says hey Andy I got to lose 25b
in 4 weeks you'll get that weight of
them oh that yeah that would be very
reasonable and then they'll probably put
on 30 pounds afterwards and that but the
lesson from that is that that same
system does apply to the everyday person
if you try to get this weight off too
fast which a lot of people
do what most likely happens is that you
end up putting on more weight yeah and
then it starts this cycle and the reason
for it is you're losing too much weight
too fast so this 0.5 to 1% per week
seems to be a very effective number that
you can aim for that will help you keep
that weight off awesome if you're going
more than that you also start bringing
up injury risk things like that if if
somebody doesn't care say uh they just
have to hit a weight they're six weeks
away and they just want to hit a certain
number on a scale because they got a a
photo shoot they're going to do or a
family vacation they're not even an
athlete but they just want to get some
weight off in the next four to six weeks
are you that concerned with them going
over 2% there'll be the rebound effect
on the back end let's we got to be real
about that but I I guess what's the
higher number you think would be like
all right we're not worried about
performance and this is not long-term
sustained weight loss but like what's
the number you'd think is is pretty high
but still manageable is it still that 2%
yeah about 2% I feel like you've been
reading my inbox Andy because I had
about three Brides messaged me saying
this exact thing for the wedding but
yeah over that 2% I don't love but you
can do it you can go up to three to four
but then look you did what 10 kilos with
vul in three days or something like yeah
something outrageous we did yeah I think
yeah something something close to that
it was outrageous but the thing is what
people need to understand like what I
said at the very very start you look at
these UFC fighters and and you probably
get all these messages as well when we
do these weight Cuts say with vul when
we lost it was something like 26b in 10
days the majority of that is water
weight though it's not like you're
losing the body fat cuz you just simply
don't have the time to be able to do
that it's a long drawn out process and
when we say if you worked out that
number oh you'd work out that's five 6%
per week that vog loss you go no 90% of
that we dehydrated him and that was done
in a very controlled environment and
it's quite dangerous and I probably
wouldn't put you Susie who's about to
walk down the aisle to your Forever
partner I probably wouldn't put you
through that same process so I'd say
upper limit probably about two to three
but yeah like I said I prefer to go the
sustainability route we do work with a
lot of guys like even actors have to get
ready for rolls and whatnot and then
that dehydration you can do you just
need to know how to do it safely and
what limits exist for your body because
yeah it's very likely that an actor
isn't in the same shape and has the same
experience as a UFC fighter so you're
probably not going to be a to hit the
Volcan OSI 26 pound method as well yeah
totally okay so going back to our
assessment piece uh resting metabolic
rate calculated one way or the other the
next part of assessment you talked about
was really proofing the pudding like
what is actually working and one you
know some of the stuff that we pay
attention to I'm sure you do the same is
not only the body weight but then how's
your performance right uh are you at an
acceptable loss of performance right so
when you go into goric deficit you're
hoping to still maintain or improve
physical performance you can Define
performance you know however you want
and whatever realm you're in but there
has to be some range of saying yeah
we're losing the weight but we're not
getting the training adaptations or the
volume or whatever
metric you're putting on there and then
the injury rate right outside of that
like I'm pretty okay with it right so as
long as you're not getting hurt and our
performance isn't getting killed and we
are losing weight then we're okay
anything else that you guys really pay
attention to the only other thing and
again I'm banging on the the mental side
of this a lot just because I know it's
important for people how horrible are
you to be around because that's
important right because you might be
getting good strength games in the gym
how horrible are you to be around
because it's a real thing you might be
get good GES in the gym you're getting
more shredded you're whatever else like
you're still sleeping well your energy
levels are good but if your mood is up
and down and crazy maybe there's some
things within the diet we can rearrange
to help that that in itself is not
sustainable and then I think well if
your goal is to be a terrible human that
no one wants to be around then yeah for
sure keep keep on that path but we
probably got to fix that as well so
that's the only other thing that we do
monitor because it does happen a lot
where people are like man this is just
really tough and I just can't handle
these mood swings outside of that I'm
sure there are a host of questionnaires
that you ask and preference and medical
history and there's all that that goes
into the equation what they like do they
have any allergies so on and so forth
but is there any other additional
assessment stuff that that you would
really like to do or are we ready to go
on to kind of the next part of
interpretation I think the only other
thing and I mean this is definitely in
your wheelhouse handy is just even a BL
basic blood work panel I really do do
like getting that only because if people
come to us and they go hey I do want to
lose weight I'll for sure take you
through a weight loss protocol but I
want to make sure that you're healthy
before we do that because we know if we
put you and we get the numbers wrong
which touch would we don't but if we put
you in too big of a deficit we can throw
out some of these biomarkers and at the
end of the day you're probably losing
that weight because you want to be
healthy so let's do it in a way that's
healthy and we need to have a way to
track that so you know we aren't too
intense with it but something as simple
as a complete blood count and just
making sure say if we've got a young
athlete that's coming in hey is your
iron levels all good if we've got
someone who doesn't get out side of lot
is your vitamin D levels good because we
want to make sure we've got all those
Ducks lined up so it gives you the best
chance when you go on this weight loss
regime are you going to have all the
chips lined up for you to do well Dan
will always say that people often times
want to lose weight to get healthy but
some folks have to get healthy first to
lose weight right if you are in really
tough spot for a number of different
areas physiologically and then you go
into a deficit on top of that you can
expect a crash and burn real fast it's
not going to play out well so that
that's great to hear um with the blood
work you're probably looking for just
kind of major red flags right just are
you way off on any metabolic profile any
Endocrinology way off the board like
that's you're just looking for kind of
screeners yeah exactly and again it's
not really my wheelhouse and if we
something is really there we just prefer
onto an endo or or someone like yourself
but this the big one one's complete
blood count where we're just looking at
basic things like your blood lipids are
we looking at your fasting glucose for
guys are we looking at your testosterone
are we checking your B vitamins your
vitamin D status your thyroid status
mostly because there things if we do
retest and you've got access to that and
say 8 weeks and we go hey the weight
came off but hey look your blood panel
is all over the place yeah you lost the
weight but we're not healthy that wasn't
the goal so we need to figure this out
how can we do this so you are healthy
when you get those data back to you how
are you using that to specifically
construct these individualized plans
yeah so again comes back to the goal so
like let's say Andy you want to lose
weight and we go okay Andy's come in
we've run the numbers you've gone to a
testing center you got your RMR next
thing we need to go hey Andy how do we
make this work for you and we'll run
through this process again okay Andy
needs to lose x amount of weight we've
got 2,300 calories okay Andy's goal is
that he doesn't want to right back to
your talking about start with protein
get he doesn't he doesn't want to lose a
lot of muscle mass he want to lose the
body fat so to me I go okay then we
should probably push that protein a lot
higher he's resistance training 2.5 g
probably as a minimum I would say for
Andy okay let's look at the fat hey Andy
what's your preference with food do you
like fat but oh yeah it's all right I'm
not too big on it okay let's make sure
you're getting some natural healthy fats
here we're setting that about 1 gram and
then you go okay Andy let's see how your
intake is what's your relationship with
carbs do you like taking in carbs and
that's how we're setting this up what I
generally get guys to do though because
this is a big part of it as well is I
say hey Andy just before we get this
started track two days of food for me
just track two days of food one I want
to have an idea of your style of eating
do you have a preference for when you
eat and whatever and does that align
with your goals if you I've got I've got
no issues with fasting eating windows or
whatever you can do whatever works for
you but does that align with your goals
that's what we need to make sure and
then when we're working out these
numbers the foods that you're putting in
or the food you have access to are they
going to align with this or do we need
to make some shifts or is there some
education basic education on the food
that you're eating that you need to know
to be able to do this and that's a big
one that we probably don't spend enough
time on I think just in general people
go into the weeds of do this fasting
protocol do this specific type of fat
whatever but just basic education on
what is in the food that you're eating
I'd say eight times out of 10 when we
get people to track they can we go
through this with them they go oh man I
didn't realize I was having this much
fat I didn't realize I was having this
much sugar I didn't realize I was doing
this and they go what type of foods are
you having you go oh man did you realize
that tiasu even though it's a protein
tiasu has all of these calories they go
oh my God no so just starting with that
Baseline education really really
important and I'm definitely not a stick
like I was a weight category athlete for
many many years so I understand when
you're strictly like tracking your food
and you're watching every gam I
understand what that can do to your mind
and I work with so many athletes who
have problems with that but in saying
that it is a very important tool to have
very very important tool that at your
Baseline you know what is in the food
that you're eating have you noticed
frequency of feeding personally I like
high frequency you don't have to have
that general population for weight loss
for muscle like there's it in there but
for your high performance folks whether
these are your athletes or your just
people who are competing and training a
lot
have you noticed any Tendencies with
frequency or would you say the same is
true in general population like hey
these people can eat one meal a day or
two meals a day and just be fine and
what have you noticed just in your
coaching practice I've definitely
noticed with the athletes very very
difficult to achieve the training
nutrition goals which I'm sure we'll get
into definitely if we're just doing one
meal a day or if we're eating you know
doing the 16 hour fast every single day
if you're fasting find it very very
difficult to achieve just the preiner
and post training especially most
athletes morning session afternoon
session if not a midday session in there
so if you're fasting for two of those
sessions you're probably not putting the
fuel in and at the end of the day people
will say yeah but you're getting in at
night and you go yeah for the most part
you're getting it but that's maybe like
70% of it but then let's look at you're
an elite athlete we want to get these
adaptations we want to get every percent
that we can get and we need you to be
able to fuel so that you can do the
volume of training at the intensity that
we need you to do and if you're going
into this session fasted maybe you can
get through the morning session maybe
that big meal at night Gets You Through
the morning session but when you get to
that midday session you're going in
depleted and you're not getting the
adaptation that we want and then it's
very hard to refuel you in the 2 three
hours that we have before that evening
session so the frequency for our
athletes way more often and it's a lot
more and when we go through it you'll
see it it's before every training you're
clustering these little strategies
around training when we look at everyday
people especially when we look at Weight
Loss goals in my practice I find there's
two types of people the ones that really
love fasting and the ones that don't and
so the guys that like fasting it does
work and I think it's a great way for
them to control their overall calories
and say they have more flexibility if
they're doing say a 30 minute gym
session after work that works great for
their mornings yeah but for the other
person that may not work especially we
work and I'm sure you do as well lots of
CEOs busy professionals where their
morning is their most by far the
productive time and for most people I
feel when you wake up from 9: to about
midday your most productive hours and
you're doing the meetings you're doing
creative work we find that if you're
fueling that properly with these more
frequent meals you're just better in
those areas because we're getting
glucose through the brain you're doing
all these other things so there's two
types of people the ones that love fast
and the ones that don't I find the
people who like fasting it's a easier
way to control calories more often than
not it also and I think this is a big
psychological side of it oh man I just
survived till 2 p.m. hat on the back
well done I just won the first battle
okay now I can go do this it's it's
almost like this self fufilling okay
we've got this type thing and that's a a
big part of it and if that's you and
that works for you and that allows you
to again be sustainable with this weight
loss and your overall dietary habits and
you can get that 90% go for it today's
episode is sponsored by ag1 ag1 is a
vitamin mineral drink with probiotics
prebiotics and adaptogens initially I
was extremely skeptical of ag1 as I am
with all supplement companies but after
months of discussions with their lead
nutrition scientist and the general team
at ag1 I've been impressed by a1's
commitment to sourcing the highest
quality ingredients and constantly
updating their formulas to have the
right ingredients in the optimal amounts
by now it is abundant ly clear that the
gut microbiome plays a critical role in
everything from body composition to bone
health to mental health and the
probiotics and prebiotics in ag1 help to
promote a healthy gut microbiome improve
digestion reduce food cravings and
increase short chain fatty acids which
play a critical role in regulating
metabolism and immune responses it's for
these reasons and many others that I
personally take ag1 almost every day now
it's of course not a replacement for
eating whole healthy foods but it is a
great way to make sure that you're
plugging in any gaps in your nutrition
to improve your energy bolster your
immune system and just generally help
promote a healthy gut microbiome and
more if you'd like to try ag1 you can go
to drink a1.com perform to receive five
free travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2 again that's drink
a1.com perform to receive five free
travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus
K2 let's jump into I actually want to go
through your fueling strategy because we
went through that you wrote on there
that the goal was somewhere between 6 to
8 G per kilogram of body weight for
carbohydrates is that sound about right
where you want and then you wanted about
60 to 90 gram in the three of
carbohydrate again in the the 3 to four
hours before and then an additional 30
grams you know 30 to 60 minutes before I
know it's individual some I'm sure you
have athletes that do better on less
carbohydrates some that do better on
more but um why those numbers is that
pretty common where you like to start or
you just kind of personally a little bit
of a a weirdo with carbohydrates or how
did you come up with these numbers I
think I definitely a little bit of a
weirdo but there is some um some logic
behind this easiest way I guess just
quick recap on exercise metabolism how
our body uses fuel because it's
important to understand why do you
choose these numbers why do you hit this
so when we're exercising our body has
three options so we got three options
think of it like buckets so we've got
this big bucket of fat around our body
so we all have fat around and we have a
lot of it so our body has about
depending on your size and body
composition about 100,000 calories of
fat there that we can use as a fuel
source then we also have another bucket
which we call our glycogen levels and
all glycogen is is stored carbohydrate
so we store in our muscles and we store
it in our liver so in our muscles we've
got about 400 gram depending on size
that's about 1600 calories in your liver
you've got about 100 100 gram or so so
400 calories and that's of your glycogen
and then all through our body I like to
call it the highway of the body is our
cardiovascular system our circulatory
system which is our blood and we have a
little bit of glucose in there so but we
don't have much we only got a few grams
so let's say about yeah yeah 16 calories
or so so the goal is when we're
exercising and if we think about okay
what happens when we exercise so at rest
we're burning mostly fat at lower
intensity exercise we're burning mostly
fat and then as the intensity of that
exercise comes up our body starts to
rely more on carbohydrates and there's a
crossing point and it changes for each
person but we call it the crossover
point at about 60 to 65% of your V2 Max
you're predominantly going to be burning
carbohydrates so that's going to change
for everyone but about that point and I
think it's important to explain to
people before we get into why you choose
these numbers when you actually sit down
and do the mass of okay well 60 to 65%
of my V2 Max maybe not everyone has
access to testing to go get their V2 max
if you can just do some simple equations
again you just do a simple equation say
220 minus your age you get to this
number if you work out what that range
is and then you find out where that 60%
is yeah you're talking about heart rate
yeah you're talking about heart rate if
you're 40 years old 220 minus 40 put you
at 180 So in theory your maximum heart
rate should be in the neighborhood of
180 beats per minute so what is 60% of
that yes that's what you're talking from
your resting and say your resting is
like 60 to 180 whatever for most people
that 60 65% sits around 145 to 150 and I
only say that because I think when we
talk about okay I'm going to go into a
fat burning exercise they think that
okay like my heart rate has to be like
resting yeah and you go no no like that
is like only a bit more than resting by
the time and I'm sure you're pretty fit
too Andy my zone to and you know I've
spent years as an ultramarathon I've got
a pretty good aerobic base in my zone
two if I'm at 145 that's my zone two
technically but then I look at that and
I do the math I go oh man I'm getting
very close to that 60% of my V2 Max yeah
so even on my low and slow runs I'm
still using quite a lot of carbohydrates
to fuel that activity do you happen
there was Data actually but do you know
what the caloric or the carbohydrate
expenditure is on like an Olympic
marathon in other words like what
percentage of their energy is coming
from carbohydrates during a you know two
hour and 10 minute Marathon do you have
the number it's well over 80% I I know
that when you look at kogi and these
guys they're operating anywhere between
90 to 93% of their V2 Max which means
they are burning almost exclusively
carbohydrate for the entire Marathon
yeah and and the reason certainly not a
fat burning exercise yeah and the reason
I say that I think it's important to
preface it because some people look at
what you just read out and they go man
that's a lot of carbs but then we go hey
like let's look at these buckets of fuel
that we're using when we're exercising
and so for that example so that's a high
Rock session like I said at the start
you do one km run and I'm a pretty all
right Runner so I'm running at a pretty
good pace and then my partner is very
good at the machine so I'm trying to
keep up with him as well so we're going
quite hard like your heart rate is
getting up there I know for a fact that
okay I only have a finite amount of the
bucket that has glycogen an even finite
amount in the blood glucose and I've got
lots of fats basically negligible blood
glucose yeah exactly but then you okay
I've got all these calories from fats
but if we look at the intensity that
you're working at I'm probably I'm going
to be using them but not that much so
now I'm stuck with this smaller bucket
of glycogen in here and what happens
then is that and I think this is
important for the everyday person when
you work out these numbers just say
you're doing moderate intensity exercise
your liver glycogen can probably last
you about 100 minutes or so moderate
exercise and then your muscle glycogen
moderate exercise
maybe if you're lucky 2 hours maybe if
you're lucky and then your body's never
going to let you get all the way down no
and if anyone's ever run a marathon or
done a half marathon and they've heard
the word hitting the wall I don't know
Andy have you ever have you ever
experienced this no personally not but
we have seen people within probably 300
to 200 yards of the finish line of a
marathon and they can't take a step yeah
so I've seen the wall hit it's horrible
I remember very distinctly the first
time happened to me and I completely
stuffed up my fueling hence why I have
plans like this now completely stuffed
it up the only way I can explain it is
it's horrendous yeah and it's horrendous
for a way that you know you can keep
going but for whatever reason your body
just does not want you to and you
probably know a lot more about Central
fatigue and the systems of fatigue the
reason why it's important that you fuel
properly is because when this bucket
this glycogen bucket gets low and for
reasons that we don't completely
understand yet either when that gets to
a certain level you fatigue really
really hard and mentally exercise gets
very challenging and anyone running a
marathon and you usually see this we
call the 30 km Mark of Doom at a
marathon if you haven't fueled properly
by the time you've burned through that
liver glycogen that muscle glycogen
usually about 30ks any marathon in the
world people are just falling like flies
yeah it's because this muscle glycogen
gets down y so then bringing all all
that back and we go okay for this event
that we're doing what's the goal so I
look at this and I go okay in this event
I could probably run this and I'm
probably going to be operating for just
over an hour okay got about an hour got
about an hour but then I go okay I'm not
doing this as a walk in a park I'm a
pretty competitive guy and there was two
sets from my team and we had a wager
whoever wins gets the Christmas bonus so
I had some pretty big motivation to get
in there and so we were going so well up
to that 85% of your V2 we're working at
so at that point you're just ripping
through this bucket of glycogen so
you're ripping through so then you go
okay how do I best feel that how do I
best feel that activity when I go in I
go well it makes perfect sense if that's
the intensity that I'm working at
there's the volume of about an hour
which we said at moderate intensity I've
got about 2 hours but if we're really
going hard we're going to be turning
through that glycogen and we know that
when that hits a point not empty we
don't completely let's just say even 20%
from empty I'm I'm going to be done I'm
going to have to wind it back so let's
do our best to avoid that from happening
and that's essentially what performance
nutrition is and that's what that plan
is is I go okay the day before because I
know that when I eat all these
carbohydrate takes about 24 hours for it
to get in my muscle to get in my liver
so that when I sit at that start line
I've got that fuel ready and so that's
what that plan was the day before 6 to 8
G per kilogram was all about okay for
this just over an hour that I'm
absolutely going crazy on this event too
crazy because I wanted that Christmas
bonus MH and then what can I do to put
my body in the best position so that's
the day before eating that's where we
get the 6 to eight 6 to8 gram per
kilogram okay before we go on to the uh
three to four hours before a quick
question on that regarding your food
choices um
tiasu oats lobster roll sports drink why
not have higher quality foods why why
are we having so much candy and sugar
and crap and garbage in there where do
these food choices come from very
difficult to get that amount of
carbohydrates if I was just to eat say
quo and brown and rice really tough
really tough and to be fair I feel like
with that even that type of approach I'd
say still an 80% I actually bought one
of the dieticians from my team and he's
a phenomenal chef and I made him cook
for a which was great and he made like
all of those yogurt bows the tiu are all
made from natural Greek yogurt and all
these great things I was saying that as
pejoratively as possible yeah and the
thing is but even when I'm doing that
you need to get the sport strength you
need to have a little bit of candy
because at the end of the day when I go
and I go to bed I go did I get the right
amount of carbs in so that when I go to
that start line I've got it in and Andy
the other part too is that this has got
to go through my 30 ft of digestive
system and then I've got to run an event
where the toilet's over here and there's
cameras everywhere I don't want to have
to be running off or knock wood that
something bad digestive happens so then
your choices as well if I'm having these
quinoa bowls these brown rice lots of
fiber that's going to have a digestive
issue well let let's do some quick math
here um what are you in the neighborhood
of what 60 kilos in body weight that's
70 70 okay so 70 * 7 will make it that
easy we'll split the difference between
6 and 8 so 7 * 7 you're looking in the
neighborhood of
you know how many grams of carbohydrates
you H 500 gram about 500 yeah you're
going for 500 grams of carbohydrate if
you bring along for the ride with 500
grams of carbohydrates of rice and
potatoes you're probably going to be
looking at 60 grams of fiber more maybe
yeah like that's going to be doubling
your normal input right so you're going
to have a real real fiber issue uh to
your point so it just this is not what
you'd be eating to work you probably
didn't eat 6 to8 per kilogram today for
for our conversation but this is fueling
for the 24 hours for a purpose it's
always about context right so I think
one of the things that sets the work
that you do with performance nutrition
apart from day-to-day nutrition it's
understanding that there's not just bad
foods it is what's the pro what's the
con of the food and then how do we use
these things not just the calorie count
not just the macronutrient what's the
fiber content what are the other
constituents of it and how do they land
in my stomach versus fuel my performance
and all those other factors so these
distinctions are critically important so
you hit easily 500 gr of carbohydrates
on that day um one point that that has
actually come to my attention here like
I I don't want people to get too bogged
down in these numbers these are your
numbers for your body for one it's the
concepts that I want to get me to right
if you're fueling for a similar type of
event or expenditure this is the type of
strategy you would go to right so I know
this these exact numbers W apply to many
people not many of you are doing this
competition but it doesn't necessarily
matter right it's the strategy here of a
I've got an all day weekend tournament
I'm going to go do right I'm going to it
would be the same answer right is there
so 500 grams of carbohydrates for you um
what do you think your protein was on
that 24-hour period you know probably
ended up about two gram two and a half
grams I think I hit so probably about
140 so pretty high still yeah pretty
pretty good amount pretty high and then
you fill in the rest with fat which is
like sort of reasonably low whole foods
for the most part but a couple of other
little bonuses and stuff in there and
you still got again rice and lamb and
bananas and honey and all the stuff's in
there okay so that's the the day
strategy as we reiterated that's not
your normal eating strategy that was
your fueling for performance if you're
eating that every day when you're yeah
motivated to get
there we're going to come back to the
gut training the gut is very important
and I'd love to hear more about that and
we're going to contrast this by the way
in one second against another example um
that that I have of fueling a very
different way but why the 60 to 90 grams
3 to four hours before yeah so let's go
back to like this bucket analogy right
so we got the bucket big bucket of fat
but we're operating this intensity we're
probably we're going to use some but not
all of it we're going to use mostly this
glycogen bucket but like I said before
cardiovascular system that's your
circulatory system that's your blood is
just passing oxygen and nutrients to
every cell in your body even when you're
exercis
and one of those nutrients that it's
passing is glucose and it can pass it to
the working muscle now we Noti this that
in your muscle so this Bucket over here
of the glycogen that's inside your
muscle and that's going to start working
as soon as you get going and like we
said before when that gets down to a
certain level that's not a good time
when you hit that wall not a good time
one of the strategies that you can use
to delay or spare that glycogen
depletion is you can top up your blood
sugar even though it's not a lot like we
said it's only about 4 G or so not very
much going around in there but if I can
put in 60 to 90 G and then I'll explain
why we choose that amount too the theory
is is by the time that breaks down we
get that extra glucose in our blood that
can go to our working muscle and our
muscle can help use that and that takes
the burden of using this glycogen bucket
that takes the burden off so now I've
got two types of fire in the furnace
because I'm operating this high intens
it's coming down and I'm playing the
game of as soon as it gets down here
we're not going to have a good time so I
need to slow down the rate of which it
gets down here the reason we say 60 to
90 gram is that when you eat food it
doesn't just go straight into your blood
we have to put it in our mouth we have
to chew it has to go down our esophagus
it goes into our stomach and then has to
pass into our small intestine the first
little part of our small intestine is
where it will cross over into our blood
now the way that our body crosses that
over we have one type of receptor that
will take one type of carbohydrate which
called glucose and then we have another
type of receptor which will take
fructose so fruit sugar over and we know
it's in the way I describe it is imagine
having a driveway and you've got one car
parked and it's a Ono driveway very hard
to get a second car in there right you
have a twodo one you can get two in so
that's the theory is that if we can do
about 60 G through one driveway we know
we can get about 30 G through the next
driveway and so we're not backing up
that one driveway which means less GI
distress more efficiency that we can get
that in Peaks our blood sugars spares
that glycogen Happy Days Let's Race for
a Christmas bonus why does it caus g
distress if it doesn't get out of there
it's backing up right and what we call
glucose is what we call osmotically
active and it's just a fancy word saying
it attracts water yeah so if it's in our
intestine there and it's pulling water
in
that's not a good idea when we're
running slushing round the idea with
these carbohydrates is we want to get
them through our body into the blood to
the working muscle as fast as possible
if they're hanging around it's not a
good time the the average number that
we'll throw out an exercise physiology
is that rate of getting glucose out of
the stomach and into the circulation is
about 60 grams right that's sort of the
max for glucose MH but because fructose
has the independent receptors and their
rate is about half of that about 30 what
you're saying then is if you add and you
did say 90 G total but you did it all
from glucose you wouldn't be able to get
all that that's the one car analogy
right you would get backed up so 60 that
would get out but those remaining 30
would stay in and they would continue in
the GI track which would then pull water
into it and now you've got diarrhea
right that that's what's going to cause
it so by switching that type of the
glucose out to fructose it'll be able to
cross over through those independent
receptors there not leaving a bunch of
sugar in your stomach pulling fluid in
and causing the the GI distress right so
wonderful example actually there taking
direct science stuff and putting it
right into practice and resolving
problems
there on that note then you go 30
grams uh 30 to 60 minutes before you
you've already just smashed 450 calories
or grams rather calories grams
throughout the day you put another 6090
in why the 30 minute top off cuz I
really really wanted to win this
Christmas bonus but again if we think
about it okay the driveway like you said
we' put it through the receptors
hopefully that's going round in the
blood by then what I can do then right
before we tell this to a lot of our
endurance guys right before you go to
the start line grab a gel put it in
because what you can do then is you can
start trickling in some more Yep blood
sugars to go and Spike it up and then
that's available as well so we know that
we've got enough time for that one that
was 90 minutes to pass through our
stomach get into our gut hopefully be in
the blood supply it's going around hey
they're clear now those receptors are
clear let's get a little bit more in and
then the idea behind that is the more I
can get in there the less I have to use
from my storage over here because once
this storage goes down kaput it's a hard
time to keep that intensity of work so
we can just make the most of that
science knowing we can get that
receptors working and we can get that
food through and then we can just sneak
a little top up in before stop okay
amazing there two questions one
regarding the gut and and how do we get
people to this level if they even need
to be but before that really quickly
what were those actual food sources for
the 3 to four hour prior as well as the
36 minut what were you eating exactly do
you remember examples yes I don't you
guys don't have do you have pet here I
always say this to Americans and they're
like okay they're mini pancakes must be
an Australian word yeah so mini pancakes
essentially so which is predominantly
out glucose sauce cut that up and then
we just have a banana on top and then
we've got so whole food here this is
your thir 3 to 4 Hour this is the yeah
yeah exactly beforeand then we've got a
little bit of Honey on top okay very
very easy and super easy to super easy
and there's a lot of carbohydrate we're
getting about 90 G in there it's very
light it digests very fast probably 5 G
of fiber in there yeah not much at all
very very low fiber and it's and it's
quite tasty too so it's like you can put
it down and cuz I've done this for years
right I've done it for years training
early in the morning it's hard to eat in
the morning like I don't care how often
you do it you can train it but it is
tough and doing things like that where
it's a low volume it's uh low fiber and
it's quite tasty makes it so much easier
just to put it down especially when you
come down oh God I got to do this I got
to stretch I got to do everything else
very very hard if you've got a big dense
meal you've got to put back so if you
can keep it light something like that's
so so easy and it ticks those two boxes
so it's super simple yep and then what
did you have for that last 30 minutes
sports drink sport strength just for two
reasons make sure that you're well
hydrated before you start and it gets
those extra carbs in we don't need to be
pushing that receptor where we're going
to the upper limit where we're going to
the 60 that's just 30 so we can just
sneak him on in there and any sports
drink certainly not the nonzero ones or
the zero calorie like we definitely want
the calories at this point this is the
the entire idea at that point you want
to be looking at just 30 gram 30 G of
glucose not going to depend as much if
it's glucose fructose if you can just
get 30 grams there avoid the non- sugar
ones because that's exactly what you
want you want the sugar when you start
getting
past in an example of an hour you're not
really going to be running out of body
fat you have no chance right this is can
you handle the suffering can you fuel
when you get past a couple of hours when
you get past many hours now you have an
entirely different Challenge on your
hand so someone like Ned who had love
fore to share what he did challenges
start to come and now training the gut
starts to really matter right because
we've got a handle there so if none of
that made sense friends Jord is going to
explain it to us here and and I'll make
sure those questions do clarifi but who
is Ned Brockman and what in the world
did you do with him and oh my gosh
that's one of the craziest things I've
ever seen in my life yeah Ned's one of
the craziest guys I've ever met in my
life and he's 25 that's the craziest
thing that probably explains it okay
yeah yeah so Ned Brockman is a
Australian Ultra Runner and what he did
two years ago is basically ran from
cottis slow Beach which is in Western
Australia right across Australia to
Bondi Beach which is on the other side
so he ran what left to right across
Australia yeah yeah yeah through the
middle of it through the middle and and
if you know Australia you've ever been
99% of us live on the coastline and in
the middle there's a whole lot of
nothing and he ran through a whole lot
of nothing and it took him about 43 days
and I guess 43 days 43 days how many how
many kilometers was he running a day I
think he averaged about he was aiming
for 100 by the end of it probably just
shy of that around 90 or so unbelievable
a day and that's that's what his first
challenge that kind of made Ned Brockman
become the guy he was and he goes you
know what how am I going to Top This and
there was an old record set by a very
very famous um Greek Ultra marathoner
where he ran a th000 miles in 10 days a
thousand miles in 10 days yeah so yeah
100 miles a day for 10 days Crazy Feet
crazy crazy crazy feet Ned took it upon
himself and said you know what I'm going
to give this a crack I'm going to train
for this and I'm going to give it a
crack so what n did in October this year
is there's a big event down at Sydney
Olympic Park just doing laps Sydney
Olympic Park and we ended up we ended up
going we didn't hit the record but it
was the CRA one of the craziest things
I've ever been a part of ended up going
for about 12 and a half days running
around in a circle around Sydney Olympic
Park in case you're half asleep he ran a
thousand miles in 12 and a half days on
a track okay so I got a bunch of
questions on this what ultimately we're
going to get back to is how the fueling
strategies changed for these but I think
I think it's important to talk just a
little bit more about what net actually
did here because I'm just genuinely
curious so uh you answered one of my
questions like how much was he sleeping
and it's about 8 hours and was he
sleeping right there in the track or was
he going home or like what happened he
was I don't think there would be one
night he got close to 8 hours to be
honest it would probably be close
anywhere from 2: to maybe 5 if we needed
it halfway through we needed to call it
a bit early but again like anyone who's
ever done any they didn't have to be an
ultra endurance athlete just a tough
workout pretty hard to sleep afterwards
everything's going no way so yeah
probably averaging between 2 to 5 at a
good night sleep and let's be honest
it's not going to be deep restful sleep
so he's doing that but then running wise
the goal was 100 miles a day which is
160 km what it ended up being more
realistic once it all played out ended
up being about 120 km per day and you're
just out there for 16 hours there's
toilets set up at the venue two toilet
so if he needs to Veer off we've got a
tent set up where his sports sports
medicine team so myself his physio his
other crew are all in there and we're
constantly making food he's getting
physio attention we're changing shoes
We're addressing issues we're doing
strapping whatever else and we're inside
the Olympic stadium so for a couple
hours each day all the Public's allowed
in to come watch him and then we've got
access to change rooms which at the end
of each day Ned comes off the track he
gets on a wheelchair we wheel him back
in under the stadium into the change
room he eats his food he has a shower he
gets wheelchairs to bed he sleeps for
sleeps for however many hours we've got
wakes up at 5: a.m. back on the
wheelchair wheelchair back out to the
track gets on starts going 6: a.m.
doesn't want to take a step that doesn't
count towards the 100 miles exactly or
the Thousand Miles right exactly can't
blame him 100 miles is a long way to run
like if you think you just run a 10K
which is like six miles for the average
person you're pretty sore after that so
imagine running 10 times that and then
doing it for 12 and 1/2 days so even
after the first one you're feeling it
and even after that and I say this to
everyone who gets into ultra marathon
the pain never goes away you just get
better at dealing with it so even if I'm
running a 100 mile race it's still hurts
after 20 km like your knees and
everything still your body is just
probably a bit stronger and you're just
better equipped to deal with that so Ned
would have been hurting from day one
even halfway through day one even a
quarter way through day one it starts
hurting and the body starts breaking
down the other thing that we always say
with ultra endurance events especially
not just a fueling but particularly from
a fueling perspective is that everyone
loses in Ultra endurance oh yeah you
just have to slow down the rate at which
you lose so we can get to the Finish
point in whatever time you need to get
there and that's what the game was with
Ned how much time did you have to
prepare him did you guys do anything or
was from your perspective was it just
show up race day and then just try to
keep him going no God no I I would have
said no if they called me in last minute
we probably had it was a good amount of
time I'd say well over 6 months of
dedicated training just for this okay
you had a long time then long time and
we needed a long time to be honest
because Ned's young he's 25 so there was
a lot of things we needed to do just
from basic nutrition like I spoke about
with the the tracking and going through
an understanding food I had to go
through all of that with him so I needed
him to understand what it is that was in
the food that he liked eating and if
this is your goal to do this this is the
type of foods that you need to eat and
this is the way you need to eat to be
able to achieve that Ned also young guy
like 25 he had all these preconceptions
about food as well and then looking a
certain way we basically had to sit down
go man like this is about performance
this is an insane thing you're going to
put your body through ditch that we've
got to just think about optimal fueling
and getting you through that so he was
really good though like Ned I think is
one of those guys is that he's Elite in
a lot of are is but he's very elite in
how he takes on information and then how
he applies it and that's not just his
nutrition but that's with his physio his
strength conditioning his run coach
everyone and he's really really good and
over that six months we were able to one
establish a really really good daily
eating plan which is important if we
come back to that first point that
energy availability making sure that
he's not in a point where he's in what
we call low energy availability which
then causes something we call Reds
relative energy deficiency syndrome
which can cause all sorts of problems
bone fractures illness gut problems
don't hormones go into zeros exactly so
last thing you want when you're getting
ready to run a th000 miles so that was
first how can we get these calories up
here and then it's okay dietry control
like you said we want to get good
quality diet because the stress you're
putting on your body through this
training period is through the roof and
he also had to get used to this very
bizarre sleep schedule where every so
often and he would do a training session
where you'd wake up bang 20ks out go
back home bang 20ks out 4 hours later go
back home 6 hours later bang 20 and it
was through the night because we would
be running through the night so he had
to get used to that as well so all of a
sudden there's all these additional
stresses that we need to take into
account and so it was getting his
day-to-day diet right he wasn't that big
of a carb guy beforehand and that was
one of the big things we worked on was
man like if you want to get through this
event and we'll talk about why they're
so important and use this bucket analogy
but you've got to get very very
comfortable with consistently eating
these carbohydrates and that was a big
challenge that we had to do the reason
we did that is because we needed to
train his gut to be able to handle that
and I think we'll go into training the
Gap because I think it's very very
important and it's this concept that
it's it comes from competitive eating
and I'm sure a lot of people are
familiar with the hot dogs chicken wings
you know when they just and they just
smack it back right and you look at that
and you go how does that happen and us
as Ultra endurance athletes look at that
and go yeah that seems really important
because that's essentially what we do in
these races like an ultra endurance race
is essentially a moving picnic you need
to be able to just keep eating because
you there's no way you're putting in the
amount of fuel that you're burning so
with Ned we're going okay man this
strategy that we've come up for you
involves you pretty much every between
15 and 30 minutes putting something in
your mouth and you're going to have to
do that for 16 hours every day for 12
and 1/2 days so that's a lot of pressure
and stress going through your gut your
gut can handle it but if you and me Andy
right now we go hey let's go down to the
running track down the road we'll grab
some Chipotle and grab some burritos you
and me would be throwing up on the side
because our guts just can't handle it's
not trained for it so that was a big
Focus okay Ned doesn't matter if you're
going for a 5K run or if you're going
for a 50k training run every opportunity
you're moving is an opportunity for us
to train this gut so I need you taking
on certain fuels I need you taking on
carbohydrates in a event that long that
goes for 16 hours a day for 12 and 1
half days is a bit more than just simple
carbohydrate gels every 15 minutes that
would feel terrible we need to be
getting in whole meals and we need to be
getting in protein we need to be getting
in fat as well so we were making sure
that Ned was stopping and getting pies
and meals and chocolate milk and things
that he could just get used to okay I
just ran 30 km I need to stop eat a full
meal and now I need to keep going and
then we'd review had it go what worked
what didn't work oh the liquid carbs
don't sit too well okay let's change
this up okay these electrolytes weren't
too great we need to really dial this in
and the thing is when it comes to the
big day you do all this prep and anyone
who does an ultramarathon will
appreciate this is that you can have the
best plan in the world and then what's
that saying from like tyon everyone has
a plan till you get punched in the face
and when you're in an ultramarathon
everyone gets punched in the face yeah
but as his performance nutritionist I
can be confident that we can still pull
it off if we've nailed the principles so
even if there's great plan that I spent
all these hours conducting coming up I
go to offer him the food he looks at and
goes N I go oh great that's okay so long
as his gut can handle the food that I
want to put in and I've got options to
give him which is essentially what ended
up happening so we spent all this time
one making sure that he had enough
calories throughout a day get through
relatively injuryf free I'll say
relatively because no one's getting
through that training block completely
injury free not being sick was a big one
and then being able to recover from the
training and we talk about a lot you
know recovery is I would argue more
important than the training that's where
the adaptation occurs if we're trying to
get this guy's body ready to be able to
run 1,000 miles he needs to be able to
do the training for him to be able to do
the training he needs to recover
properly for him to recover properly he
needs to eat properly so huge huge
effort just to get him there it was
almost like an ultramarathon before we
even started yeah but it was a it was an
experience as a doctoral student uh I
had a friend who was now we were in a
lab that had a a long history of
exercise physiology and Sports Nutrition
so Dave costell who who did a lot of the
preeminent work in the 1970s and ' 80s
on what carbohydrates are and fats for
fuel and a lot of the initial work with
Frank Shorter and Steve Prefontaine and
some of these endurance people so like I
kind of came through one of these
Hallmarks of legendary Sports Nutrition
despite that as doctoral students not
even grad students as doctoral students
my friend was running his first marathon
I think and I remember us sitting kind
of in these carols and a bunch of us
were talking about you know fueling and
when and what and how much before and
exactly the types and things like that
and he had this whole plan
and we were I want to say we were like 3
weeks out from his race and I remember
just asking them man just like curiously
like well what have you been doing in
your training that worked really
well and he just went like dead silent
and he looked right at me and he's just
like I I haven't tried any of it yet oh
no and I was
like so you're about to go into your
first marathon having not tried any of
the strategies that we have now been
like design design for him it wasn't
part of our lab it was just like a side
thing and that was another reminder to
me and I was coaching athletes already
at the time but I was just like how in
the world would you come up with an idea
and then try to go put it into practice
without ever trying so when you're
you're talking about how like the
strategy you come up with it means
nothing until you get out there I mean
gez six months of trial and error with
him and then you still had to change it
mid-
race like anyone who's done anything
like this would would say yeah if you
told me otherwise I'd say you've never
done it right cuz you'll they'll have
that pretty consistently so I think what
I I probably should have done is taken
your high rocks taken Ned and then put
something more in the middle right
because these are both very extreme
which is fun right I actually like this
a lot you have an hour competition you
have a 12-day
competition if you were to take somebody
doing more of a classic say three to
five hour thing right this is the the
amateur person doing a a marathon or um
like an Olympic triathlon something like
that like in that mid-range the concepts
are still going to be the same here but
it will be slightly different right in
your case of your hour competition you
didn't have to worry really about
training your gut in terms of in
competition right do you remember what
you had in terms of fueling in that race
or you kind of just like drinking taking
drinks of water and I didn't didn't have
anything right purely because I knew you
know what and probably overdone it to be
fair and I think I was just doing it
proof of concept whatever but I had all
the fuel like I knew the buckets were
full and the thing is I felt great like
and there were guys in there who
definitely did not feel great but I
think it's an important thing as well
Andy and I always try to like make this
point as well when we talk about fueling
for performance and everything and like
let's say um so say if you and I went
for a run and went for a 10k run and are
you a run Andy I don't know okay okay
good this makes this example a lot
better so so I've been running for years
and I've done a lot of it so I'm pretty
conditioned for running right so if we
go for a 10K or a six mile run and we
say hey Andy let's have a race I'm
putting my Christmas bonus up for this
let's let's have a race okay so we're
both I see your point it's coming into a
competition right and then we go okay
let's go and I'll go we go for the run
and let's say okay I win and then we go
okay no no let's make this more fair
then and we go okay Andy I'll fast so
I've got none of these buckets full
nothing's full I've got no fuel on board
and then Andy you can eat the tfd Jordi
salivan best fueling diet the Ned
Rockman strategy I'm going 750 yeah
you're going the High Rock eating
strategy we rock up the next morning to
that race who wins yeah you're still
gonna Crush I'm still gonna win right
because only because I've been
conditioned over years my muscle
fibertite my you know Energy Systems my
better aerobic base my anerobic
threshold all of these things are just
more conditioned I think this is an
important conversation to have
especially when we start talking not so
much about the elite athletes but more
when we go okay for the everyday person
who wants to do this because at the end
of the day you can eat the best diet in
the world but doesn't necessarily make
you good at the sport what makes you
good at the sport is training and I
think that's where you've got to put
your thought process and you've got to
go okay if training is what makes me
very good at this Sport and my goal is
to beat Jordi in a 10K and take his
Christmas bonus then I need to focus my
training on doing that and nutrition
comes into play by helping me train more
intelligently and helping me recover and
rock up and train consistently that's
where nutrition comes into it we're
going to finish this conversation on
that exact point which is daily
nutrition versus training nutrition
right because that's a really excellent
thing I love how you brought that up I
actually wish I would have started this
entire conversation off with that
concept and Concepts like this because
on the same point this was competition
day for you this was not a training day
so my assumption is you probably did not
eat this every single day you worked out
right so there's also a difference
between if you and I said hey let's go
run this 10K
and let's just go here we're we're
hanging out together let's just go have
some fun let's go run a 10K that's not
how you would strategize right now if
you said let's run this for a Christmas
bonus this is how you strategize right
yeah so there's a difference in fueling
for an activity and fueling for the best
possible score you can get in that
activity right so that is a very
important distinction because I'm sure
you know some point in this conversation
people are going to be you potentially
triggered or something to say like you
couldn't do this every day like no this
is not intended to be done every day
this is fueling for performance to get
the best out of there we will definitely
again talk about how does this fold into
a day you brought up one little Point
earlier and I want to Circle to that um
and you actually said it really cleverly
but you might even want to change when
you're eating your calories throughout
the day to still be in something like a
caloric balance but have a a pseudo
program like you develop for your higher
rocks right so can you jam a bunch of
calories in around your training than
getting some of the performance benefits
but then still having your calories low
to lose weight so we're going to get
into all that stuff um but I I don't
want to I got a bunch more Ned Brockman
questions for you um to get to there so
that's really great with the six months
of training all right now this is
actually nice because this is a little
bit more like a daily rather than a race
day right so I want to chat about the
race Day stuff but for that six months
of
training do you remember roughly what
the the calories were per day and as
well as the macros and then how long did
it take you to kind of figure out those
numbers so we obviously periodized it I
think just General within the week every
day we we want to be aiming to have
about 4,000 calories and he what how
what's he weigh probably closer to 60
kilos oh he's a bit heavy he's a tall
guy he's deceptively tall like he looks
really skinny but he's just de I just
assume if you run an ultra like you're
under 100 I mean like isn't I tell
myself that 57 is like the perfect
Marathon running Champion height cuz I'm
that
I'm not a good run though but Ned's
quite tall Ned's um about 62 so he's
about closer to fluctuates anywhere
between 79 and about 82 kilos yeah big
guy wow okay so he's reasonably big so
about 4,000 calories yeah um roughly on
the days and what uh how many grams of
carbohydrates he's averaging he was
depending on the training day say on a
higher end would be about that 500 G of
carbs you'd be doing roughly 160 g of
protein and and then fat he would have
been doing yeah whatever theing there is
yeah whatever the filling and I guess
that comes back to your point with the
the clustering because if you look at
that like we was saying oh you can't eat
that every day in your training you got
to understand though when you're doing
the volume that Ned was doing to get
ready for that you can what was his do
you remember what his weekly volume was
it was some weeks he was doing up to 200
km crazy right like yeah crazy amount of
volume and this is the thing though is
that obviously when the volume goes up
and all the intensity goes up you have
to increase your intake and so when
you're doing something like that even
the 500 G of carbs we still had to
titrate that in because he wasn't used
to it and a lot of those carbohydrates
not like he's sitting down every single
meal and having huge amounts of carbs a
lot of those carbs were clustered around
these workouts and if he's going for a 2
three hour run we're using these
principles of the 60 to 90 G to get his
gut and those Transporters used to
taking in different types of
carbohydrates so a lot of that 500 is
coming in around that training whether
it be that immediately before training
so we can Spike those blood sugars or
during training so we can just keep them
consistent to help spare that glycogen
so a lot of that intake is clustered
around his training how much of it are
you trying to get in before those heavy
training sessions versus afterwards in
other words are you like hey you got
this big mileage today let's get you way
ahead of the game or are you more Pro
post actively saying okay you ran these
numbers we got to back fill that stuff
in yeah I think combination of both
right depending on the day but genely
say if you're doing 2 three you're going
to get pretty close to winding that down
so your overall intake for the day needs
to be quite high but we like starting
pretty heavy just front loading pretty
heavy for the exact reason that you said
that we've got two training sessions
here we're going to burn through a lot
even though I know you don't need it for
that first one I know for sure you can
get through but we're not thinking about
just this first training session we got
session number two and we got session
number three and the thing is and you
know this just as well as I do Andy and
all your athletes would say it it's hard
to eat after training just all the
hormones going you're tired you're hot
whatever it's tough so if you can
frontload it and get on top of it early
I found it's a lot higher chance that
you'll actually hit those numbers cuz
500 gram is still a lot to be eating
yeah that's a ton okay we got those
basic numbers I'm sure they change dayto
day but we can we we get the gist of it
when did you start the the race
preparation from the food perspective
was this 7 days out was it just the 24
days out when did I guess the food start
changing when you Caro which is the
process of trying to fill up this
glycogen bucket so it's maxed out so
when you start we've got maximal stores
here you have to practice that a lot to
be okay with it come race day so what
would we would do with Ned is that if he
had a long run on a Saturday I mean
every run for him was a long run but a
longer run say on the Friday we'd
practice his car load strategy so his
gut was used to it that was basically
the only thing that we changed was
beforehand we did it for two days
actually so a 48 hour Caro and we're
hitting so I was hitting numbers of 6 to
8 gr he was hitting between 10 to 12 G
per kilo so much higher because the
whole question is is like is that too
much to max out the glycogen I sit back
and go I don't really care because we're
about to do this for 12 and a half I'd
rather overdo it than underdo it well
what's the worst thing that will happen
if you overdo it yeah might on the
toilet bro right and in practice this is
the time to learn because if you were to
look in the scientific literature you
will see 6 to 10 is is the number we say
for crazy events like this but that's
just a guess he might be 12 he might be
14 he might be five like you actually
don't know what his upper limit would be
until you've run that experiment right
so you have a starting place which is
what every good scientist does the
literature tells me to start somewhere
between 600 to 8 right that's what you
did that's what you did with him but the
literature doesn't tell you this is the
only number you have to ever be at it
doesn't say this is what's going to work
the best it just says on average most
people will probably do pretty well at
this number but I think that's really
smart of you to obviously I'm not
stunned at all you did that because he
could he might be fine at 12 he might be
fine at 14 I definitely know we've had
people well over 10 and they're like
absolutely fine from a gut perspective
and and I know certainly some people
will be just destroyed at that number so
very smart on you to to try that and see
where you could get to um what was the
kind of heist you got 12 or so about 12
for two days before we got about 12 G
per kilo and I guess that's a good point
to Andy that's guys that's that is a
kilo oh huge of carbohydrates oh huge
amount he's 80 kilograms 10 would be 800
gram right if he's close to 12 like he's
getting close to a th000 grams or a
kilogram of carbohydrate yeah and this
is the thing back to your point about
like the literature as well you can look
at that but and and we can dive into
this a bit more when it comes to okay
what do you actually do during an ultra
endurance race a lot of this endurance
literature that you're reading for the
most part is done on Elite male marathon
runners who are running between 2 hours
and 230 marathons which is very very
different to running 1,000 miles over 12
and a half days the same so a lot of
these principles even when you're going
intra fueling like your electrolyte and
hydration strategy how you're car
loading a lot of it like you said is up
to your interpretation and that's a big
part of why we said we need six months
here because yeah we've got some guiding
lights here but this is a pretty crazy
event and I'm looking at the physio
going have you ever done anything like
this he's going nah and it's like the
coach have you ever done it's like nah
and we're all going okay well what do we
use as our guiding lights and you're
doing this but really we need him to put
it into practice we need to get some
feedback and then we need to adjust and
then keep going and that's why we needed
so long in the prep yeah I mean the data
on Marathon running would be almost
useless at this point you you need to
look at cycling yeah right that's
probably the closest thing where you
could get is you know tour to France
being the more Prim one there's other
races but those databases what those
coaches do throughout that fueling
strategy is probably much closer to what
you did here and even if we're looking
at cycling because we didn't but just
overall power wattage for say someone in
the tour to France greatly different to
someone who's plotting along for A
Thousand Miles so when we look at that
and you go okay how much per hour carb
do we need these guys in the tour to
France in the pelaton are pushing 20 G
plus you got guys in 100 mile races
breaking World Records doing 120 g plus
does that apply when we're doing you're
referring to 12 G per hour per hour of
carbs yeah during the race in the race
yeah and that's what a lot of that oh
it's incredible but then we go does that
apply over here for Ned and so that was
almost the other part that was really
exciting about this whole thing is we
get to find out okay actually so that's
really interesting I'm trying to guess
here I might be wrong but let me know um
so then was the strategy hyper fueling
his carbohydrates Before the Race but
then maybe not even having a huge amount
during the race basically I guess to the
everyday person like for me and you if
we ate what he ate we'd go oh that's
that's a lot if we compare what he did
and we can go through his numbers to say
what someone in the Pelon or these
really really Elite you know Zach Miller
Breakin world record alter endurance
guys do basically half in terms of
carbohydrates per hour so he was 50 60 G
per hour yeah I think we averaged about
68 G per hour which is still pretty good
for people who have played basketball
yeah or football or like they've never
done any real endurance work you would
be like wow 60 grams in an hour that
like that's quite a lot but it's really
not if you contrast it to like the
cycling and and other long duration
Sports where you're going to be over 100
theoretically yeah grams per hour okay
super interesting so going back to it uh
you tried out multiple times the 48 hour
window and you're getting you know 800
plus grams of carbohydrates in in those
days um is that what you also then
eventually did before the race yeah
before the race yeah and it worked well
in the way one way very unscientific way
which is still scientific is when you
eat a lot of carbohydrates you put a lot
of glycogen in here and we abuse this
with our Fighters All That glycogen
holds water as well your weight goes
right up so your weight will go
skyrocketing so then I knew if his
weight went up to a certain amount to
about 83 84 kilos
I knew that okay we're pretty good here
so in the 48 hours before competition
you were trying to get a three kilo bump
in body weight thereabouts yeah
something in that neighborhood maybe a
little more three three and a half kilo
which is I don't think people would
think about that right that weight gain
that you get in the load is
exceptionally important especially when
you're digging through the literature as
well and you're looking at say these
Marathon guys and so and a lot of it
right when we're talking about okay and
and we we'll talk about this essentially
like I said at the start when you're
doing an ultra marathon everyone loses
our job is to slow down the rate that
you lose and Ned was in one of those
very interesting scenarios that not a
lot of people put themselves in where
these buckets are going to get pretty
close to empty even if we just let Ned
run around the laps and keep going yeah
these glycogen buckets and the glucose
bucket go down he would start
drastically going into the fat bucket if
we didn't fuel him we just ran that's
why if you go out for 5 days have a
little bit of water you're going to
eventually drop you're going to just
deplete all your stores as well that's a
real possibility the thing is our goal
then is how do we keep these stores high
enough and how do we keep his system in
a spot where he can just keep going and
a big part of that which we'll get into
is the hydration piece but what a lot of
the research and there is some good
research that does account for this now
is that and you would have heard oh the
2% if we lose 2% but they're looking at
marathon runners say that they don't
account for this carbohydrate load and
then they weigh them at the end of it
and an elite marathon runner running
220 if you've ever run at that pace even
on the treadmill for two minutes I could
probably do it for a minute you're not
stopping and drinking a lot you can
maybe Swig and go and you see that with
the elite guys as well so they're losing
quite a lot so that's a factor we had to
think about as well cuz then we're going
okay the literature is saying that a lot
of these Marathon guys can you know
there's the study of um Gabrielle celesa
I think he's in the 2004 Dubai marathon
where he lost 10 % of his body weight
and he broke the world record oh there
there's stories like going back to the
Frank shers and stuff of 5 L per hour
like getting dumped in fluid just huge
fluid losses yeah and you look at that
and you go okay well 10% we've got heaps
and you go well that's probably a lot of
that is like the pre fueling so like in
an event that goes this long what are
actually the boundaries that we're
working within to keep him going CU
again that's the game right the game
here isn't we're trying to we were
trying to break a world record But
ultimately we're trying to just keep him
going so and then there's not really I
couldn't find any any literature that
told me how to feel Ned Brockman for
this but you're trying to interpret all
of these things from this research that
does apply but kind of doesn't and then
we're all sitting here as the sports med
team going okay how do we do this how do
we do it what are we tracking what are
we looking for his weight goes up here I
know for a fact that when he comes
around and we'll doing weight checks as
he was coming around if I want to keep
make sure that he's not depleting and
he's not becoming too dehydrated what
weight do I go from then but knowing
what his regular weight was in that
six-month prep and getting a good
average gave me a good number so when he
came into the tent and we're tracking I
can go okay we're on track here okay so
just to make numbers up here you're what
you're saying is you knew for six months
that he's going to weigh roughly 80
kilos all right I want to make that
number up and then you knew when he
started the race he was 83.4 something
but you were not going to base your 2%
loss on that 83.4 you based that 2% loss
on on the 80 kilog right so the 2% loss
to clarify is the marker of hydration
right so once you get below 2% and we're
not saying 2% dehydrated it is you've
lost 2% of your body mass right and
we're assuming most of that comes from
from water below that 2% performance
decrements are going to start going down
right so we will you know with with our
competitive athletes we'll certainly get
well past 2% but we're not competing
right then right we're going to go away
we got 24 to 36 hours to rehydrate so
the 2% number is based on that 80% did I
have that exactly right okay so as
you're watching him and you start
noticing he's down to whatever that math
works out to be but he's down in this
example say if you had a weight check
and he was 76 kilos you'd be like whoa
okay now we know we're in a danger spot
because we've lost way too much fluid at
this point yeah so you were giving him
enough fluids on top of the food to keep
him you know RI plus or minus that 80
kilograms so you knew he was going to
lose three or four what did he end up
being about on I would imagine after two
three days it did kind of stabilize
probably till the end or so this is the
craziest thing and this is why I give
Ned so much credit he did stabilized and
I've I've got the numbers he basically
stayed around 7879 and he never dropped
below 2% and the reason for that he had
a fantastic hydration strategy and
that's not me saying I put into place
that was him executing it and he
executed it perfect practice for like
that is an execution 100% so his weight
never went down do you know offhand how
much total fluid he was consuming per
day it ranged between 500 Ms and about
1.2 lers depending on the weather total
throughout the day oh per hour sorry
okay all right so between a half and a
little over a liter per hour while he's
running while he's running for the most
part okay and that was enough where he
could not feel like he's sloshing around
in his stomach but then also getting the
fluid in that he needed to get in yeah
and again that was part of the
assessment we do and I have this
philosophy and and I'd love to hear your
thoughts on it too Andy is that if
there's one marker that you can use to
tell how well an ultra endurance Runner
will go it's their sweat rate yeah oh
yeah and I think if you've got a low
sweat rate everyone would know those
guys and Racers that rock up to Aid
stations and they just oh bit of
watermelon great oh shish kebab I'll
have some of that chocolate orange juice
and then they run on their merry way
because what they're losing is very easy
to replace and they're never going in
past these two point
2 to 3 to 4% dehydrated so they're never
getting to the point where this is
getting really stressful on my system
and we're getting all these
cardiovascular problems plasma volume's
going down we're not profusing to the
gut all these problems they're not
getting there because it's so easy for
them to replace it when you get these
really big sweaters completely different
these are the guys that are dragging
their feet into the aid stations they're
overheating because they're dehydrated
even if they're drinking a liter of
fluid per hour they're still not even
meeting 50% of their needs big big big
problem that was the first thing I
looked at with Ned and he fortunately
was a very low sweater he'd only lose
between 4 and 700 700 M an hour if it
was really hot oh if it got really hot
while he was running he'd get up to
about that 1 1.2 yeah yeah and he within
that limit you can basically use that
drink to thirst to an extent y to an
extent you can use that drink to thirst
which Ned did use I'll say he did use it
but then again it was educated because
we spoke about it and being like if I
left him to his own devices he just
wouldn't drink so he was a wary hat to
do it but once you get past those areas
where it gets really really big losses
it's very hard to drink to thirst for
one and it's very hard to just meet your
fluid demand and like that rate of
losing just Rockets down it's a really
big challenge that was the first thing I
assessed with Ned when we did that I
went okay this is going to make this
whole thing so much easier Y and did you
just do that assessment via take your
body weight go run for your hour come
back in check your body weight again
okay you're down a kilo we know you've
lost a leader or something like the way
we do it is that and you would know this
for sure with weight cutting I think
weight cutting with these athletes and
for the guys that don't know who are
listening weight cutting is when we put
the UFC fighters in the saer or the
bathtub and they sweat a lot I've spent
years doing that with hundreds and
hundreds of athletes and I feel like
I've got a very very interesting
perspective on sweating and heat
tolerance and everything that is hugely
helpful for these events but what you
know and I know Andy is that the first
hour that you exercise you lose quite a
lot yeah the second hour you lose a bit
more not as much and then it goes down
it cuts in half about every hour yeah
and there's osmotic reasonings for all
of that it's interesting in Ultra
endurance because unlike weight cutting
where you're knil by mouth not putting
anything in you are over here yeah so
you're influencing those osmotic
gradients that are affecting that so
what we do with our Ultra endurance
athletes hey Ned give me 1 hour at your
normal Running P that we're going to be
doing this race at okay that's what you
lose in your first hour give me one
after your 2hour run and then go out for
a 4 five 6 hour run record everything
you're you're putting in and let's see
how this changes because that's
important as well if we just do the
hydration strategy for that first hour
we're probably going to overshoot your
hydration as we get past the 6 Seven 8
hour mark that's going to create issues
in on itself yeah so we need to
understand what does your sweat rate do
during the duration of the event but
then also what happens when the sun
comes out and you're in exposed Sydney
Olympic Park and it's 32° how does that
change your sweat rate compared to there
was one night we were there and it got
down to 9° and you're getting extremely
cold you're not sweating at all y so you
have to understand okay what's the fluid
and electrolyte strategy for all of
those situations yeah we uh we don't
play around with that as in we measure
it directly in real time at all times so
especially you know fight week or
competition week during the Olympics and
things like that um we will wear at all
times a NYX andx sweat sensor I don't
have any affiliation to that company we
just buy them like everybody else but
you can put that on and you can see in
real time exactly the sweat rate total
sweat amount and the sweat content so I
know at all times when our Fighters are
doing weight cut stuff I I don't have to
have them step back on a scale I
literally know exactly what they way the
entire time through so there's no
guessing at all there and that sensor is
really cheap it's like $100
or something over here so you can you
can do a bunch of different things like
that to to not master we do it a bunch
in Camp as well because you're right it
will change when you change the scenario
the sweat rate the sweat content will
all change as they've sweated more that
sweat rate will go down that decay is is
pretty easy to actually plot we'll
actually do that like almost always is
we'll plot that decay ahead of time so
I'll know where we're going to be at I
mean you know all the numbers on your
guys too like there's no guessing
anymore at this point but um you happen
to have any idea of how much like sodium
you are putting in per day or any close
to that cuz you can put back a liter
water per hour but if you're not putting
in some sort of electrolyte you're going
to be in problems especially after 12
days worked out to be about 550
milligrams which is pretty good yeah
pretty low though for per hour per hour
yeah okay well per I guess liter of
fluid that we'll put in in probably a
better way to put it yeah yeah yeah okay
that's that's a that's not a crazy
number yeah at all I mean that's going
to be a crazy number multiplied by 10
hours but really five gr that's not that
much so he is a pretty low sweater and a
low sodium sweater and this is the thing
that I found with pretty much all our
Elite endurance athletes they all fit
that Mark really is that they're a low
sweater and they're a low salty sweater
but every single one of them will tell
you that they're a really big sweater oh
I know every single and it's funny
though and this is segueing a little bit
and this is a sentiment we both share is
that it's not that you're sweating a lot
you just feel really hot and you're just
associating feeling really hot with
losing a lot of fluid but they're not
the same thing so I got a really good
sense of what he was drinking and his
electrolyte on there um what did his
fueling look like uh throughout the the
actual race event here oh man this is a
it's very eclectic yeah so I'll give you
fatigue right yeah I'll give you kind of
the daily rundown and it's it's a bit
odd and people are going to listen to
the first meal and be like what the heck
and I'll give you the reasoning for it
so don't shoot me down straight away but
so first meal on my job when he came in
I'd wake up about 4:30 so we'd get home
about midnight and then I'd wake up 4:
4:30 and I had to be back at the track
at 5:00 he'd start at 6:00 a.m. and um
crazy enough this a little segue the
first two laps that he did he would
describe that he had to slam his feet
into the ground he wouldn't run he would
slam them into the ground so that his
feet went numb so he didn't feel them so
he could run normally so we'd Rock up to
the track and I'd have his breakfast
with me and I just hear
this and I look at him it's just this
guy head down just banging this and then
afterwards I kind of said some people
are like that's the first 15 minutes of
my day yeah yeah and then he and then he
had to do another 15 hours of that but
he said if I didn't do that my feet were
in so much pain I couldn't run but
anyway I digress I would rck up the
first thing I had to do and the only
thing he wanted to eat after about day
five or six was I guess McDonald's he
wanted a McDonald's but he would wake up
that's not the first thing he'd woke up
and he'd have an oat bowl so he'd have
this big oat bowl and we'd aim to get
about 120 g of carbs and he'd have oats
he'd have milk he'd have brown sugar
banana berries maple syrup we'd add to
it bit of protein powder he'd have that
he'd have his electrolytes so he could
get back up and be hydrated another 500
milligrams of electrolytes yeah there
abouts yeah there abouts and tried to
aim for train I assume your product yeah
yeah so he'd drink that and then he'd
get back up he wouldn't get back up he
would be wheeled he would wheel out to
the uh track and then we'd start going
and then after he did I think it was
eight laps I'd have to be there with his
first meal and the thing is is that that
would sustain him for a little while but
all of these Ultra endurance events you
just get onto it before it's a problem
you have to do it and the thing that he
could only thing he could stomach was
these the McDonald's um McMuffins that
as well as hot cakes drenched in syrup
which got a lot of and he even said he
even said to me like man I'm never
eating this food again and it's like and
I get it because he doesn't eat that in
his dayto day and his mom looked at him
at one point he said look honey it's
serving a purpose and it's working so
let's keep at it and then a lot of
people will say like oh why didn't you
just give him these Whole Foods and do
this and and like don't get me wrong we
Tri them we did we absolutely did in an
Ideal World I would give it it's just
not realistic not when you've been going
for that long your brain is just so
fried and 600 mil in and the other thing
Andy that people don't appreciate with
this is that there's a lot of sodium in
those Foods no doubt a lot of sodium and
people will go everything else in his
life was sweet at that point exactly so
it's like we're ticking two boxes where
I don't have to give him something sweet
on the pet and I don't have to rely on
giving him salt tablets which when
you're taking salt tablets as well they
can have that osmotic effect as well you
can get in the food it digests better so
a lot of the sodium we were giving him I
was trying to get in the food and it's
people look at it and go oh what you
can't that's unhealthy and you go for
that point in time that was the best
thing he needed and the thing is it got
him through and he doesn't eat like that
for 99% of the other time but that's why
his gut can get away with it cuz he's
trained his gut very very very healthy
all the time but yeah Big oat balll and
then we'd start with McDonald's and then
we'd kind of just rotate between we had
so many different options we'd go from
like custard bowls like yogurt bowls
we'd have shepherd's pie we'd have oh
man all sorts of food like you think of
it we made it and it was just like we
were getting fresh food bought in like
meat pies like baked
goods um like veggie slice all types of
different things we had pretty much the
goal of okay every 40 minutes or so if
we're aiming for about 70 G we're
getting in like 30 to 40 gr of carbs
every time he takes something in and he
eats so whatever we were making in
concocting we had to like run the
numbers and we had um his mom and then a
couple of the crew members there and we
had a big run sheet so every time they
would write it down I'd kind of go past
and be like okay let's work this out
where are we at did he get it in okay we
didn't get it in that round this next
one let's add some say whipped cream or
something light or maple syrup honey to
the banana bread just so we can get
these numbers back up y cuz like I said
this is probably one of those situations
where these buckets over here we're very
much depleting them so he was eating
about every 40 minutes about every 40
minutes so the way it worked is that
every two laps he'd take on hydration
and he'd swap between Water and Electric
light es and then every eight laps or so
which worked out to be about 40 minutes
we'd give him a little something to eat
and then after 32 laps he would come in
and sit down for a meal proper meal
makes sense so what were his total
numbers at on those days in terms of how
many total grams carbohydrates and
calories and things got on my phone can
I pull it
out's I wrote These down all right so
nerd's daily nutrition so we were aiming
for about 8,000 calories a day what we
got in okay so even uh you doubled his
normal Daily Style that was the target
the idea yeah and just on that note
8,000 do the math I'm running for 16
hours a day 100 miles you're burning way
more than that yeah we are absolutely we
are and this is why this is important
that we have a strategy to make sure
these buckets are full because in the
background where we're making up the
difference is this bucket of Fat Y
that's where it's coming from and what
we need to do and why we're putting so
much emphasis on the carbs is because
this is what's keeping him going because
yes we're burning this fat almost in
double time while he's running and just
to make up the energy difference so it's
literally like I keep saying everyone
loses we're just trying to slow down the
rate at which you lose so you can get to
the Finish Line carbs we were averaging
just shy of 1100 G 1100 G 1100 grams and
which worked out per day to be 13 grams
per kilo per day that was the strategy
yeah that what you actually executed
that's what we executed yeah wow that's
pretty good though that's yeah insanely
good like I said hugely impressive from
him um protein 307 was the average which
was 3.8 G per kilogram per day why so
high on protein we had to make up the
calories to be fair because otherwise it
would be one I think the lean muscle
degreg was a big problem he had in his
last race and so a big focus in his
block was putting on a lot of muscle Y
and then I was very very aware that
we're going to still and I'm talking
about these buckets muscle is a bucket
as well that you don't usually tap into
I was very aware that he would start
tapping into oh yeah I mean again this
is where you will differ from even an
Iron Man right where you're not
concerned about protein intake from a
muscle preservation perspective at an
Iron Man because who cares right doesn't
10 hours Breeze not a big deal you had
to do that for 10 straight days 12
straight days yeah exactly it's just a
different bll so that's actually
interesting I never thought about that
because at that point you absolutely
have to be worried about it right yeah
um when you do just on this protein
point when you yourself or have coached
other folks doing a more traditional
Iron Man or maybe honestly a 50 or 60
mile ultra what do you normally like to
have them at for protein intake we don't
particularly look at it too far in depth
unless it's above 100 km so 100 km
you're getting anywhere done between 12
and 16 18 hours if you're doing like 100
mile and you're going into the 24 to 36
hour that's when we look into it so sub
10 hours you don't even care yeah we're
not really looking into it and again I
guess the other part to that we won't go
into it is like the frequency of racing
which comes into you're doing these big
training blocks which are going to be
very very muscle atrophying so it's like
we need to look into it so but we're
still not aiming for crazy big numbers
if I'm being perfectly honest well I
mean honestly generally people do pretty
low protein yeah at this point right
because you're trying to get in fuel
you're concerned about getting calories
so fat will bring in you really care
about carbohydrates and protein is
usually there just to settle the stomach
because it comes along for the ride in
some foods it's it's there a part of
other stuff but so if you're doing a a
paddle board race or a walk or something
like that and you're sub 10 hours then
you know focus on fat calories digestive
comfort and not worrying really about
protein at all um what do You' like to
see past that 10hour Mark for protein is
it closer to that one gram per pound
yeah I'd say one one gram or so 1.5 is
or so yeah but in this case you wanted
to go way higher than that because a
very unique challenge yeah and and I
knew that that was an issue after his
last challenge that he had and then
you've got to put that muscle back on
afterwards right which is very difficult
so let's just not lose as much during it
this entire conversation we've leaned
heavily on carbohydrates so with this
event with maybe the 10-hour plus events
and the sub 10hour events was there any
thought to going really high on fat
particularly for this one given the fact
that it's lower intensity it's blah blah
blah blah blah um have you guys
experimented with that did you try that
with Ned what are your general feelings
on the endurance people going really
really high on fat given you know yeah
I've got mixed feelings about this I
think if you look at the literature I
think Louise Burke's done some really
really good stuff here her Supernova
studies I think are just the the great
the greatest things ever WR and out of
Australia yeah out of Australia Louis is
probably the the goat of All Sports
Nutrition and she's phenomenal and she's
studied this a lot right and it's not
that and she even says it herself it's
not that she's anti- keto or Pro carbo
she just want when you're working for
the Australian Institute of sport you're
trying to find out what works best for
the athlete to get gold medal in to win
exactly you're not you're not paid
incentivized to promote a diet like you
want your athletes I promise you right
now if I knew how to feel my athletes
better than the rest of you I would do
that I would probably not tell you but I
would have 10,00% be doing that not be
protecting a brand or like who cares
behind the curtain if you're not telling
anybody You' be doing what works the
best right yeah exactly right so yeah
she's got her incentives are to show
that you know well is to find the thing
that works the best yeah yeah and you
would have seen this when you were
coming up through University doing your
doctorate there was this whole thinking
right like out of this whole system I
just explained where okay we' got this
big bucket of fat we've got these finite
resources of glycogen there's the bucket
of protein over we're not really going
to touch but if there's a finite
resource of glycogen why don't we just
focus on the huge reservoir of fat and
get better at using that and use that
throughout the training or the add a
couple of other pieces to that actually
to make the the case for fat the other
strong arguments I hear are it breaks up
having to have such sweet stuff all the
time like you get in carbohydrates so
the pal of fatigue is one another one is
you've gotten over double the amount of
calories per gram right and so if you're
looking to try to get six to eight to
10,000 calories in a day fat is a way
easier source so those are probably the
strongest Arguments for going a moderate
to even really high fat there so that's
the argument but in theory how does it
work so in theory you can go okay if I
eat a high fat diet lower carbohydrates
I should be able to metabolize and
oxidize that fat better and then
therefore at these intensities that are
lower to the higher intensities if I'm
using more fat because I'm fat adapted I
should be going into this fat Reservoir
and using more fat sparing the muscle
glycogen I should be able to go further
for longer and I should perform better
and it's a very valid Theory and what
Louise did in those Supernova studies is
she took those Elite race walkers and
she fed them and to be fair it's 3 weeks
but she's repeated the Supernova studies
almost eight times I think yeah a ton of
different protocols the different
lengths uh in terms of Shor duration
longer duration yeah she's done it a
bunch so she took these two groups of
elite race Walkers fed one of them high
carb diet which was about 8.6 G per kilo
don't quote me on the exact number per
day so quite high so H Rock High and
then keto very low so 50 g per day and
then when it came these are Elite guys
that did this in a race to perform as
well so when she measured them she said
yes in fact when you eat a higher fat
diet and you have less carbohydrates you
do indeed burn more fat and you burn
more fat way more efficiently and then
when you eat more carbohydrates you burn
more carbohydrates so then you go okay
well let's put these guys in a race
together and let's see what happens and
every single time she's repeated this
study the high carb guys win and you go
well why is that and you do in fact see
when you track this yes these guys do o
oxidize more fat almost double to Triple
the fat gr per minute than what the high
carb group is but when you get up to
these higher intensities they one just
don't have the reservoir of fuel in the
glycogen so their body is looking to get
this glycogen that's just not there and
two they don't have the enzymatic
processes to rapidly break down that
carbohydrate so these race Walkers much
like Olympic marathoners anyone that's
really going hard in race who is getting
85 990 93% of their V2 Max you're
looking to burn and break down this
carbohydrate these guys are very
efficient at the fat but when it came to
those higher levels the high carb guys W
out and you go well can't you just burn
the fat in the same way and the thing is
people think you can't burn fat high
andt you can you absolutely can and the
difference between it is just 5.6% and
all that is is just the chemistry the
stochiometry for sure and if these go if
you remember doing you know your organic
chemistry now loved it at undergrad but
if you work out the amount of ATP which
is the energy molecule that you get per
molecule of oxygen you get about 5.6%
more ATP per molecule of oxygen for
burning carbohydrate compared to Fat
yeah so this is a really good
biochemistry point that gets lost in
people that have just a touch of
exercise
physiology if you were to take a gram of
carbohydrate and a gram of fat you would
get an order of magnitude more Total ATP
from that same gram of fat right you
would get far more there are way more
carbon bonds you'll run way more rounds
of kreb cycle dryc acid cycle and you
get way more Total
ATP but it's literally the opposite when
it comes to oxygen efficiency that's the
story that you just outlined
carbohydrate is more efficient right per
molecule of oxygen
by that exact amount this is the
difference right it's total amount of
capacity for ATP versus efficiency per
molecule of oxygen sometimes you care
about the total number sometimes you
care about the efficiency in this
particular case this is going to be a
problem even though you have because
fundamentally you're not out of fat ever
anyways that's not the rate limiting
part of burning of of Performing is not
how much fat you have because as you
shared earlier it's not outrageous to
have a 100,000 calories on your body
potential Fuel and fat but you're going
to have 2,000 calories of carbohydrate
on your body you're going to be limited
by that yeah like that's going to be
your so it's faster it's directly in the
exercising muscle tissue itself and your
stores are limited so it may or may not
be better but it's certainly going to be
the limiting factor it's going to run
out much faster right um the Supernova
studies are not perfect the the high fat
ketogenic folks love to criticize them
no study is perfect right but I think
based on all the available EV evidence
and in this at least your philosophy
with your
experience it seems to be the
carbohydrates for these kind of events
are um is that the same for sedentary
people no no no those are totally
different conversations right we're
talking about performance fueling long
duration endurance events your personal
experience with your individual clients
and uh at this point I think you've made
a pretty compelling case that you're not
no fat you're not that's not like three
grams per kilogram is not low m F that's
a high amount um but you're certainly
going to be emphasizing carbohydrates a
lot is that is that a fair summary of
your point and I think if we go back to
that point that we made right at the
start where we worked out the zone two
heart rate yeah yeah so if we go back to
that point and even someone would say oh
Ned's not running at 85 90% V2 Max I say
I absolutely agree but considering
everything that's going on with his body
cardiovascular drift the stress and
everything else the way that his
metabolism does work is he probably is
sitting in that high Zone too which we
know is still predominantly using carbs
so we can say okay well if he's going to
predominantly be using carbs as an
energy source anyway yes the fat is
really important and being fat adapted
is really important definitely but we
need the carbs because it's a finite
resource and I always say to people one
if your goal is to get fat adapted the
best way to get fat adapted is just to
train you become really fat adapted just
by train it's the best and most powerful
training response you get and then I say
okay two coming back to that point these
Ultra endurance races are really tough
and that relationship between glycogen
levels and Central fatigue even though
we don't completely understand it it's a
real thing when you've got someone
running for 12 and 1/2 days and we're
getting low on glycogen and he's
absolutely mentally losing it if I can
give him more carbohydrates and that
gets us back on track and that gets us
back going towards the goal we're going
to go with more carbohydrates and that's
something we notice every time that Ned
would mentally slip run through the
numbers oh man we didn't we missed a
feeding opportunity we didn't get this
in we didn't do this blood sugar must
have dropped and then he really
struggled he started burning into that
glycogen so and I do appreciate it and
like you said for the everyday person
for sure we can talk about the fat
adaptation but when it comes it just we
see it clear as Dave the fastest
marathon runners burn more carbohydrates
the fastest Ultra endurance athlete who
a running 100 miles at these 85 90%
their V2 Max of burning more
carbohydrates you can do an
ultramarathon just on fat absolutely
you're just probably not going to be up
there and when we say 5.6% more
efficient every single marathon world
record in the last 10 years or five six
years let's say has been broken wearing
Super Shoes yeah which add how much
percent you know to it probably a couple
of percent couple percent and then you
think okay difference right and then you
think and 100 met Sprint isn't the best
example for Energy System wise but you
think the difference between first place
and second place Place yeah is 1% so if
we're seeing that okay you can be 5.6%
more efficient and then these studies
are saying that the high carb athletes
are performing 8% better just by the way
that they eat maybe for the everyday
person if you're just trying to complete
it for sure we can we can try some fat
but if you're at the top level and
you're trying to do something insane and
you're trying to compete we're taking
that 5.6% yeah all day right there's a
difference between completing and
completing at your fastest okay
fantastic I want to touch really quickly
and we don't have a we'll have to do a
whole show on this but I opened up the
the chat today I gave the example of
your highrock fueling and then I gave
the example of kar France doing this and
it was still jelly beans parmesan
chicken coconut cookies and chocolate
grilled
salmon you get the idea here
right this was for somebody trying to
lose I don't know what it was 5 kilos in
5 days or probably something like that
he's a little bit more what I want to
know is about this 5-day process of
weight cut um not I realize many of you
listening will never do something like
this but some of you will right we have
a ton of weightlifters and powerlifters
and wrestlers and Jiu-Jitsu folks and
things that are going to could be and
those that are also just interested in
physiology like how do these pro
athletes do it I think if I would have
had a pull of people who listen to the
show and I asked what do you think a
fighter eats I don't think for you know
for this W cut none of these things
would have landed on that list 1,900
calories for a guy
um again it doesn't matter if these KN
numbers but
probably you know Monday of fight week
was 135 pounds and had to get down to
125 it's probably in the stratosphere if
not it's it's a reasonable numbers right
so 10 pounds in 5 days he ate 1,900
calories a day 60 gram of carbs 140 gram
of protein and 125 gram of fat how on
earth does that equal 10 pounds of loss
over five days so the understand this
let's break it down into two distinct
sections so we've got the fight Camp so
when these guys sign a contract say Andy
you made the UFC congrats you call Jordy
up and you go we got to make waight yeah
and you go hey Jord I've got eight weeks
okay I'll give you numbers on me right
now uh probably walking 175 and I
competed at 145 yeah okay so we get
these numbers 145 and we go okay we need
to figure out how to get Andy on weight
there's going to be two distinct I got
10 weeks 10 weeks okay two distinct
parts of this process we're going to
have our fight Camp process which we're
going to focus on body fat loss so
through that process we're going I have
none I can tell you you're looking good
appreciate it but we're going to lose
that body fat the way we're going to do
that is a sustained controlled calorie
deficit that's all the stuff we talked
about all we talked about we're going to
put all these principles of periodizing
the nutrition so can per week exactly so
we're going to use that so let's just
say 1% per week and then we go okay then
we transfer over to 9 weeks of training
you arrive to the hotel which is in the
city you're fighting in we've got one
week here then the strategy changes to
what we call the acute weight cut okay
so let's just say as an example I was on
170 right now I did that I had nine
weeks I lost 9% I don't know what the
exact math works out there but like i'
I've done this I've done this 145 pound
thing many times so I can tell right now
that's going to be 158 yeah probably in
the ballpark right so if I Monday of
fight week 158 I got 133 more pounds to
go I'm very happy with that number ex
that also then meant I lost 12 pounds in
9 weeks yeah yeah very reasonable yeah
and it's within those limits right where
we go okay that's about 0.5 to one maybe
1.5% is okay but we're happy with that I
feel like we can remove water in that
acute weight loss phase very safely in
those 5 days in those 5 days but some
guys for whatever reasons genetic
certain characteristics we might be able
to push it up to 12% after that I'm not
very comfortable with it I think so for
me um if I'm 160 10% would be 16 lbs
yeah so you'd be comfortable with me
going 16 pounds of water over those 5
days which would be 144 yeah so some
people
8% is is their you know probably their
limit which means they need to be 157 or
so some people maybe 12 would be that
162 163 so these these numbers are
lining up pretty much perfectly yeah ex
so let's just say I'm at that 160 I'm a
moderate weight cutter is I'm sort of
average and that 10% would probably I
don't have to do that like 9 point
something but let's say 10% yeah so we
got 10% here and then we go okay we need
to completely change your dietary
strategy Everything Changes at this
point everything changes so for that
change to work though in your fight Camp
you need to follow a couple principles
you need to be eating a good amount of
carbohydrates you need to be replacing
the salt that you're losing in your
training and you need to be having a
good amount of fiber and the reason we
need you doing that all through fight
Camp is because these are the three
nutrients that we're going to manipulate
in these five days to get this water out
and what we're doing in these five days
is we're strategically scientifically
but very slowly taking water out of
different compartments now the first big
change that a lot of people be familiar
with is we're reducing carbohydrate
intake now if we're reducing
carbohydrate intake if we go back to
this bucket what we're going to do is
slowly remove all that glycogen so if
we're removing all that muscle glycogen
we're removing some of the liver
glycogen we're not only just removing
the physical weight of that stored
glycogen but every piece of glycogen and
this numbers Up For Debate but I always
go with it holds 2.7 G of water so let's
just say 1 G of glycogen with 3 G of
water so by using this strategy you've
got four G here there about total weight
of total weight of your total glycogen
that we can rip out so that can
translate up to 2 three 3 4 kilos which
is you know what that 5 let's do easy
math right let's see if I dumped 100 G
of carbohydrate and then an additional
300 grams of water I just lost a half a
kilo yeah is right like I'm over if a
pound like in that in that Meetup
scenario right so I'm there yeah and to
do that all we need to do is reduce your
carbohydrate intake so we're removing
all of our grains our breads our pastas
things like that and we're replacing
them with high fat high protein foods
thing is though Andy you're coming in
you go to UFC fight in 5 days time your
coach is going to want you to train
every day and I go okay well I know that
from doing mixed martial arts it's a
very tough sport to do when you don't
have carbohydrates on board and we can't
rely on your bucket of glycogen because
we're depleting that every day so that
60 G that you're seeing that I'm giving
Kai every single day we're strategically
using one of those receptors that we
spoke about earlier to get him 60 G of
carbohydrates right before he's training
so when he goes in and trains one he can
actually train to a decent level and two
mentally he feels better so that's where
that 60 gr comes in and that is that
almost entirely coming from those jelly
beans yeah well it's personal preference
right right because some guys like they
love having blueberries and strawberries
or fresh fruit a lot of these guys you
got to remember they've come off so Andy
you've just come off nine weeks dieting
and now you're coming into this pretty
intense weight cut phase where you're
depleting your body that glucose hit is
a real thing and anyone who's done
endurance Sport and has done a
carbohydrate mouth rinse will appreciate
this even you swishing carbohydrates in
your mouth and spitting out sends a
signal to your brain and you go wow I
feel good that's essentially what we're
trying to do by hitting the 60 grams of
carbs right before training yeah and
you're depending on the size of the
person probably looking for 30 to 50
grams in that pre workout yeah sort of
thing okay so they're going to do that
and and they're going to continue that
we don't need to walk through like all
the Diesels the exact fight weight stuff
but why not just take calories we down
why not just go to 1,000 calories my
assumption is I got 10 pounds to go I
should start pulling calories way down
for this whole week right yeah because
this is the thing in that first block
that's what we were focused on right we
were focusing on nine weeks of losing
body fat to do that we need a control
calorie deficit when we are manipulating
these water this water in these
different compartments and this is going
to sound crazy to a lot of people but
you can do that independent of being in
a calorie completely independent
completely independent which means you
don't need to be in a deficit to lose
that weight and we're not saying you're
losing body fat here all we're doing is
Shifting fluid out of different
compartments for example reducing the
carbohydrates that's a intramuscular
compartment that you're taking the
glycogen out and all of the Associated
Water with it that happens whether
you're on 3,000 calories 1500 calories
as long as your carbohydrate intake is
limited and you're removing that
glycogen that will happen yeah water is
in three places for the most part right
so you're saying like these different
compartments of intracellular intitial
and then like plasma right so we have it
in there we don't want to be taking it
out of blood yeah exactly that's a
problem right so take it out of the
cells first take it out of the space and
then ideally don't go to the the vessels
at all all right so we're going to do
that I don't know if you do this or not
but I do almost every single time for
years now our highest calorie intake
will be fight week yeah for sure we're
way up calories
because you don't need to do it right
and the thing is these guys have just
trained and what do you do every other
sporting event before you compete you do
some type of taper and a load but for
fighting we don't do that you reduce the
training but it's to cut weight so by
increasing the calories you're giving
their body a bit more of a chance to
recover they feel better it's more of an
intake they're not going to put on
weight you're not going to put on body
fat because they're eating at their
maintenance calories anyway they're just
going to feel so much better and it's
such a better experience because the
thing is you can reduce the calories as
well and do all of this it's just a way
worse experience yeah for sure what
we're doing for our second step is
stripping all that fiber back as well so
we're taking that out of the meals and
because of doing that we're going to
remove all of the digestible not waste
product but we call it dead weight
that's in your gut that if you just had
an amazing big salad and veggie Bowl two
nights ago Andy you're probably still
pushing it through but it's just sitting
there and your gut bacteria just eating
it and loving it it's a great thing just
not for this particular environment just
very specific very very and I always
make this because people will always
come at me and go you saying not to eat
fiber I love fiber that's one of the
things I love fiber so don't take this
as don't eat fiber it's the best this
very specific situation we can lose a
decent amount of weight by just taking
out especially if they've habitually
been eating a pretty high fiber diet
which most of our athletes do it's just
easy weight loss again that will happen
independent of the calories you're
eating What would fluid intake roughly
be thur say Monday Tuesday Wednesday
yeah so there's a couple different
approaches you can take with this you
can do what's called uh water load which
is what a lot of Fighters do which is
basically where they'll increase their
fluid intake the theory and philosophy
behind it and the propos science is that
if I drink a lot of water even right now
we drink this water we'll probably be in
the bathroom pretty quick because our
body will sense hey there's a bit more
fluid in here we've diluted a bit of the
salt I need to get rid of it let's get
everything back into balance plma volume
got too high too fast go to the bathroom
so essentially if you do that with
increased fluid uptake so if you water
load what the theory is is that your
kidneys then go oh there's a lot of
fluid here I'm going to if you think
about that garage door analogy that I
use for The receptors use that for the
exact same of getting water out of your
kidneys and you go okay let's create
more garage doors so we can get more
fluid out and then if I strategically 24
hours before reduce that fluid intake in
the Theory those garage doors should
stay open and I should let more fluid
out in that final 24 hours before your
body goes oh wait actually there's not
that much water coming in let's close
these and go back to normal so these
Fighters do increase their water the
literature will tell you 100 m per
kilogram of body weight I think that's
okay if you're a smaller guy if you get
up to the middle weight it's light
heavyweight it's heavy weights that's a
lot what I tend to think is I go hey
Andy through your fight Camp you are
having three leaders let's just increase
it as a percentage of that so then if
that theory works out and that's the
science all we need to do to get that
responses have an above normal response
for you so we don't need to go crazy
because we can have a risk of hyperia
which is a real risk and this has
happened where people drink too much
fluid too soon and it can dilute the
salt in their body and they can end up
having a seure going in a coma
especially if they've cut salt out
already exactly so what we do is say
only one L Max per hour space out
throughout the day about 50% more than
what you've habitually been drinking
during fight Camp 50% increase yeah 50%
increase okay and um Monday Tuesday
Wednesday am I I'm still consum
consuming normal amounts of salt yeah so
for the most part yeah for the most part
and then we're going to reduce our
sodium because again everyone has an
innate sense of this if you have a
really salty meal like you go out for
Asian food or whatever you come back you
look at this scout you go oh my God yeah
Andy texts me and goes dude I'm so heavy
and you don't worry like you just had
some I don't know red cry and it was way
too salty that's going to draw water
into your body the opposite is true if
we reduce our sodium intake then we're
going to flush more water out so now
you've got these three situations where
we're reducing carbohydrates reducing
fiber and we're reducing our salt we're
slowly moving fluid out and the best
part is that we're moving fluid out from
these different parts of our body as
well so it's not so drastic on the
system so for about 3 4 days say Monday
Tuesday Wednesday Thursday and you've
been losing between 1 to 2% of your body
weight we're coming down let's say
you've lost 5% of the 10% that we need
to lose so I was 158 Monday I wake up
Thursday I'm 153 yeah pretty much maybe
152 hopefully but like something like
that exact okay and now final day I'm
going to this is when I'm going to do a
true water cut right this is when I'll
do the you know get in some calories
what I
can low weight right weight is the only
thing that matters at this point right
so I want really high calorie really
light Foods
uh fluids are what they are and we'll do
some sort of water cutting strategy
which is ultimately it's not a huge deal
if you want a sauna if you want a bath
it doesn't really particularly matter um
because you'll get that water we off
after that right um at this point the
only danger we really have is kind of
one thing right it's the only thing we
really have to pay attention to at this
point well at this point this is the
most traditional thing when people go oh
weight cutting this is what they think
of is this point right here Andy coming
into a SAA with with JY or a bath and
you're pretty dehydrated Su on I'm all
taped up exactly and you would have seen
them running on the treadmill or
whatever and say we've got 8 lb so where
that 8B comes from is not an entirely
different part but this is what you and
I would classify as the dangerous part
of the dehydration and the reason why we
used those three strategies before is
because we can slowly move fluid out and
give your body time to rebalance back
through and by the time you get here you
go okay we've got a lot of weight to
move out out this is going to get me
pretty dehydrated but we're going to do
this in a very smart way so Andy you've
come in we've got 8 pounds to go what I
now need to do is for you to sweat it
out we need to sweat it out and then we
go okay how does that happen like you
said there's a few options here we've
got sauna we've got a bathtub or you can
exercise and then I guess this is my
entire job for the last six years is
figuring out okay what's the safest way
to do this with these guys and to do
this you need to understand okay what's
the goal the goal here is that if we
want to sweat we've got to raise core
body temperature we've got to get it to
a point and we need to keep a consistent
sweat rate so that over x amount of time
ideally the shortest amount of time
possible we're losing these 8 lbs no
more no less I can take Andy down to the
scales we can weigh in and then I can
strategically do the reverse of
everything start putting the fluid back
in the carbs and everything but that is
a very very dangerous part this is the
part that I would say is by far the most
dangerous of all the weight cutting no
doubt because when you're dehydrated
you've already reduced what we call the
plasma volume where I spoke about it
earlier your cardiovascular system
that's all your blood networks that's
delivering oxygen nutrients everything
to your cells you've now reduced fluid
out of there and in order to sweat in
order to do this we've got to take more
fluid from there and we're taking 8 lbs
which is quite a lot and the crazy thing
about this Andy and you and I both share
this philosophy is that the human body
is extremely resilient to dehydration so
before you go on you just said8 pounds
is a lot uh it sounds like a lot to the
normal person in our world that's U like
I'm pretty happy you're very H because
the alternative to that Andy is that you
didn't go in with any strategy and
instead of having to do 8 lb you've had
to do 15 lbs that's or 12 pounds
whatever it was which are numbers we've
both seen many times and done and if I'm
saying eight PB is quite dangerous then
15 lb is extremely dangerous so this
Ison and a lot of where that fluid comes
from is the plasma volume which is the
fluid in our blood so it will start
coming out of that space and what's even
worse in this area is that for our body
to cool if this core body temperature is
going up the goal of sweating is for
this sweat to evaporate into this
environment and that causes a mass
cooling effect so my call body
temperature comes down the problem is
when you're in a sauna and that sauna
gets past a very low number give it I
think it's 45 de that evaporative
process does not occur and this is where
you see what we call the drip you see a
lot of Fighters with credit cards and
they're going this is great this is
great look at it it's like it's not
great because what you're now doing is
you're heating the body up but there's
no process for cooling so you're serving
the purpose of getting this 8 lbs of
fluid off but now you're entering this
Arena where my core body temperatur is
getting very hot and we're entering into
this heat stroke and potentially heat
exhaustion Arena and this is the biggest
problem we see with weight cutting very
very routine to see these guys getting
heat stroke in a saer laying on the
ground convulsing throwing up and then
their teams dragging them out being like
you okay and then be like oh we've got
two pounds to go get them back in there
and you go oh my God like and the
reality is people have died yeah people
have died doing it and that's the thing
is it's not necessarily the dehydration
that's killing them it's the
complications that have come from being
so dehydrated in that hot environment
it's not getting hot that that is your
ultimate key you will keep sweating for
a really long time cuz in reality how
hot do you have to get to start sweating
just above so if your just above your
temperature right I don't know what's in
Fahrenheit but 37° C you go 37.1 your
body goes ah it's hot let's figure this
out right last kind of question on this
what is there a number in terms of heat
because we test this I know you do as
well I've seen you post about this we
are measuring temperature at all times
like this is all I care about is there a
number on average that you're like okay
this is where we got too hot even if the
person goes oh no I feel good I good
you're like no no pull them down because
we don't want to cross this temperature
threshold is there a number you look for
you to start to get concerned maybe yeah
I mean the literature says 40 if you're
getting internal heat of 40 then you get
in the danger zone whether not the
equipment we're using we're using the
same equipment yeah that the UFC
performance institute's using as well
whether or not it's accurate at least
it's consistently inaccurate with the
same athletes that number that seems to
be the Zone where even if this guy's
extremely tough they've done heaps of
weight Cuts if it goes above 38.5 on
this particular machine in reality maybe
it is 40 but let's just say if it's at
this point and the principal stays the
same everything gets really tough and my
is that you can be the toughest in the
but as soon as your body hits that you
go into emergency get me out of here
Zone and I guess this is where the
conversation you see this a lot in
Endurance Sports too when they're
running in hot human environments what
do they do they heat acclimate and what
the theory is and we do this with our
UFC fighters and Charles St at the ufcpi
does this well I'm sure you do it as
well Andy of course you heat acclimate
to slow the rate at which you hit this
point whether this is prior to weight
cut you're doing this for 4 weeks
minimum beforehand you're getting used
to heat yeah exactly so you're trying to
instead of going directly like this and
hitting that 38.5 or 40 whatever number
that is really fast you're slowing that
curve and you're slowing the rate at
which you hit that by heat acclimating
which is exposing yourself to the heat
what you're doing is you're bringing
your sweat on faster and you're changing
the composition of your sweat both of
those things what they're doing is
making you more efficient and it's
slowing the rate at which you reach that
critical get me the hell out of here
Point yeah fully agree we're going to
we're going to leave this and and finish
this thing up but before we do that I
probably should have started this
portion of the conversation with it and
I want to make it really crystal clear
my feelings and allow you do the same
thing but I don't like the way cut I
don't want I I'm not promoting it I
don't want anyone to do this I if I was
in charge of all Combat Sports I would
either ban it or change the rules
I don't know anyone that actually does
his work that feels differently am I
correct in assuming you feel the same
way it's the worst it's the worst I
don't want to do this at all yeah so the
I hope that wasn't that tone that we had
of the sort of the positivity wasn't
interpreted that way um unfortunately
this is a necessary evil that you and I
deal with across multiple sports right
um the last thing I want to ask you
about before we get on out of here is
kind of going a a very different
direction and that is
really in if somebody is not one of
these extreme weight cut examples which
is most people and other things and they
listen to all this fueling for
performance and they say okay great like
I want to do better in my
workouts um but I also need to be lower
in calories I need to lose some body fat
can you give us some guidance on how we
would structure because you you said
these things about kind of putting stuff
around but can you give me more detail
about how I can maybe manage my calories
in and around my workouts while still
then being at a caloric deficit so I can
feel good train well but then also lose
my weight over time yeah two big things
to understand here is that your training
nutrition gets more important as the
volume and intensity goes up and when I
say that I mean and I'm not saying that
if you do work out say 30 minutes a day
five days a week that it's not important
it's incredibly important for your
health and your longevity that you do do
that it's just that it's not the same as
if you were training for 3 hours a day 5
days a week where say with Ned or these
UFC guys we really have to dial that
back in probably not super important for
the average person doing a 30-minute
elliptical workout to have to get 100
gram of carbohydrate in during that
exactly right the answer would be zero
so if if you're coming to me and you're
saying Hey I want to lose some weight I
want to do it for these reasons these
are my goals I am able to work out say
30 minutes a day 5 days a week the first
thing I'm looking at then is I'm going
the biggest gains that you're going to
get is from your overall day-to-day
quality of diet let's have a look at
that let's let's have a look at that
first and foremost and again Andy I know
it's boring and I'm saying it over and
over again but it's going through that
checklist and the first and foremost
first thing you need to do is understand
how many calories you need and if we're
saying okay that equation that we had
body weight time
40 what we can safely say is if you just
do that body weight time 30 is a good
starting point but like we spoke about
try it really truly understand what
you're putting in and then see how much
you lose because that's the biggest
mistake people make why far and wide
it's not do I need to cut carbohydrates
do I need more protein do I need fat do
I need to fast it's simply you don't
understand how many calories you're
truly getting in because at the end of
the day as much as there's all of this
confusion about calories in calories out
what constitutes it all these different
philosophies calories in calories out is
a real thing you can't change
thermodynamics what you can change is
your behaviors your relationship ship
with food the food you're actually
eating they're all the things that are
going to influence this calories in way
more so what you need to understand is
one how many calories do I need to be in
a true deficit I'll say that again true
deficit and two do I have a system to
accurately track
that so for the I hate this word average
person
though what should I dial in first my
kind of premid poost workout fueling or
my daily nutrition strategy yeah I would
say daily for sure I would say figure
out what those calories are and go
through this process and like I said the
most important thing you're going to
need is protein so I would say if you're
going to lose fat protein is phenomenal
for it out of all these buckets yeah we
can store it in fat to an in muscle to
an extent but you can't largely store it
and the way that protein works is that
it takes a lot of energy to burn it and
to metabolize it so if you have a higher
protein diet you're going to burn more
calories by going through that energy
source so if you can have a high protein
diet under a really well calorie
controlled diet that's setting you up
for success and then it just comes down
to personal preference do you like the
fats do you like carbs and then you say
okay I am training and you know what I'm
finding these 30 minute sessions quite
difficult I find it a lot easier if I
have a bit of carbs beforehand I'll go
okay that's fine let's work out what
your daily carbs are let's use those
same principles to work out are you
getting the amount of fiber more likely
than not even if you're gone 1,600
calories we can find 120 calories which
is 30 gram of carbs in that diet which
is also a medium banana for you to have
before your training whether or not
that's going to give you the big huge
training adaptation that we're trying to
get with a UFC champion or Ultra
endurance world champion probably not
relevant but if that makes you feel good
and if that makes that 30 minute
training session a really high quality
session and you burn an extra 100
calories cuz you're super motivated on
the elliptical let's do it is it
completely necessary probably not but if
that's what you need to feel good in
that training session by all means let's
do it but it all comes down to personal
preference and I know people don't like
it because they want you to be able to
say do this exact keto diet eat this
exact eating window and hit this exact
macro split and you'll lose weight the
reality is it's just way more boring
than that it's way more individual and
you need to find what works and the
thing is need to find what works
consistently yeah can't thank you enough
man coming all the way up here I know it
was a long flight um you've shared so
many things I took a lot away from this
uh I actually learned a ton about the
fueling stuff I mean I follow everything
you do and we're in the same Sport and
I've learned a ton over the years of the
wake up stuff but more importantly than
that is the actual numbers and the
fueling strategies transferring over
from science to application and how do
we cross that barrier so it's been a
really informative conversation I know a
ton of people will will take a BT out of
this so man I can appreciate and and
thank you enough for being here today as
well as all the other stuff you've done
over the years so it such a pleasure
thanks so much for having us Andy I hope
you learned from and enjoyed that
conversation as much as I did if you
want to learn more about Jordy his
Services books and working with him
directly and following along with the
free education that he provides I would
encourage you to check out the links
that are provided directly on our show
notes to all of those and more thank you
for joining for today's episode my goal
as always is to share exciting
scientific insights that help you
perform at your best if the show
resonates with you and you want to help
ensure this information remains free and
accessible to anyone in the world there
are a few ways that you can support
first you can subscribe to the show on
YouTube Spotify and apple and on Apple
and Spotify you can leave us to a
five-star review subscribing and leaving
a review really does help us a lot also
please check out our sponsors the show
would not exist without them and they're
exceptional products and services
finally you can share today's episode
with a friend who you think would enjoy
it if you have any content questions or
suggestions please put those in the
comments section on YouTube I really do
try my best to read them all and to see
what you have to say I use my Instagram
and X profiles also exclusively for
scientific communication so those are
great places to follow along for more
learning my handle is Dr Andy Galpin on
both platforms we also have an email
newsletter that distills all of our
episodes in the most actionable
takeaways we have newsletters on how to
improve Fitness in V2 Max how to build
muscle and strength and much more to
subscribe to the newsletter just go to
perform podcast.com and click newsletter
it's completely free and we do not share
your email with anybody thank you for
listening and never forget in the famous
words of Bill Bowerman if you have a
body you are an athlete